<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Elijah's nunc dimittis, or, The authors own funerall sermons in his meditations upon I Kings 19:4 ... / by Thomas Bradley ...</title>
            <author>Bradley, Thomas, 1597-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29118</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4132</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7187</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12325308</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12325308</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59533</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29118)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59533)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 204:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Elijah's nunc dimittis, or, The authors own funerall sermons in his meditations upon I Kings 19:4 ... / by Thomas Bradley ...</title>
                  <author>Bradley, Thomas, 1597-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 133 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Stephen Bulkley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>York :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Kings, 1st, XIX, 4 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59533:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Elijah's nunc Dimittis.</hi> OR The Authors own Funerall SERMONS, In his Meditations upon 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.4. <hi>It is now enough: Lord take away my Soule, for I am no better then my Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where alſo is Treated;
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Of the immortality of the Soule.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Of the ſtate of it, when ſeparated from the Body.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Of the Deſtruction of this lower World by Fire.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Of Locall-Hell, with the graduall Torments thereof.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Of the Heavens, of the Superiour World, and the Inhabitants of them, their happineſs and glory.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Bradley,</hi> D. D. one of his late Majeſties Chaplains, and Praebandary of <hi>York;</hi> and Preach't in the Minſter there, and in his Rectory of <hi>Ackworth,</hi> 1669. <hi>Aetatis ſuae,</hi> 72. <hi>Oxon. Exon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Lord now let thy Servant depart in peace, that mine Eyes may ſee thy Salvation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sic ſic juvat ire ſub umbras.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>YORK,</hi> Printed by <hi>Stephen Bulkley,</hi> 1669.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:59533:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59533:2"/>
            <head>Elijah's <hi>Nunc Dimittis;</hi> Or, The Authors own Funerall Sermon, In his Meditation upon the 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.4. the latter end of the <hi>Verſe, It is now enough, Lord take away my Soule, for I am no better then my Fathers.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe Words are the Complaint, or the Petition, or the Suite, the Wiſh, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, (call it what you will) of the Prophet <hi>Elijah,</hi> now <hi>weary of his Life,</hi> and <hi>deſiring he might dye;</hi> The cauſes and occaſion of it, you may reade in the context, and in the Chapter immediately precedent, where ye have the whole narration of the buſineſs, the ſum of all you finde in the 14th. verſe of this Chapter: <hi>I have been very zealous for the Lord God of Hoſts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Children of Iſrael have forſaken thy Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, caſt down thine Altars, and Slaine thy Prophets with the ſword, and I onely am left, and they ſeek my
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59533:3"/>life to take it away.</hi> That wicked woman <hi>Jezabell,</hi> (in revenge of her Chaplains, <hi>the Prieſts of Baal,</hi> which he had lately ſo clearly, and ſo powerfully convinc't and ſilenc't, and proved to be falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets) had ſworn his death, Warrants are ſeal'd, and Purſuivants ſent out to take him: Upon this, the Prophet flies for his life as farr as to <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> the utmoſt border of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> on the South, as <hi>Dan</hi> was on the North; yet not thinking himſelfe ſecure there neither, though at ſo great a diſtance, he takes a farther flight, a dayes Journey into the Wilderneſs, ſuppoſing haply he might finde more kindnes there among the wild beaſts, then amongſt men in <hi>Samaria</hi> more ſavage then they: But here he meets with another enemy, as dangerous as any of the reſt, <hi>Hunger and Thirst,</hi> in danger to pine and periſh through famine, his fear and haſt, not allowing him either time or means to furniſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with <hi>viaticum</hi> for ſuch a Voyage, nor the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren wilderneſs affording him ſupplies of ſuſtenance in ſuch a want. The Prophet now compaſt about with ſo many deaths and dangers, and not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which way to turn himſelf, hungry and thirſty, faint and weary, layes him down under a <hi>Juniper Tree,</hi> wiſhing, <hi>That might might be the end of his Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, and with his Pilgrimage, of his Life too.</hi> Here
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59533:3"/>in this Wilderneſs he makes his Will; Wherein, firſt, He bequeaths his ſoule to God that gave it; <hi>Lord take away my ſoule,</hi> his body to the Earth from whence 't was taken, wiſhing, That ſpot of ground upon which he lay, might be his Grave, the <hi>Juni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Tree</hi> over him his Monument, with no other Inſcription upon it, but onely this inſtead of an Epitaph, <hi>I am no better then my Fathers. It is now e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, Lord take away my ſoule, for I am no better then my Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Diviſion of the Text, I ſhall not uſe any curioſity at all, the words neither require, nor ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it. For the ſumme of them, you may call them if you pleaſe, in old <hi>Simeons</hi> Language, <hi>The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> Elijah's <hi>nunc Dimittis;</hi> Or in St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> his <hi>Cupio diſſolvi.</hi> In it theſe Parcels.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>Dimittis</hi> it ſelf, in theſe word, <hi>Lord take away my Soule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Two Reaſons perſwading him to make this his Suite at this time: The one prefixt, and ſet before the <hi>Dimittis,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Nunc ſatis eſt, It is now enough.</hi> The other annext, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing after it, in theſe words, <hi>Nam non ſum melior majoribus meis, For I am no better then my Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all reaſon, we muſt begin firſt with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Reaſon, both becauſe it ſtands firſt in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59533:4"/>Text; and becauſe it ſtands in our way to the <hi>Nunc Dimittis;</hi> and becauſe it is a motive uſhering it in, therefore of it firſt, of <hi>Nunc ſatis eſt,</hi> before of <hi>Nunc Dimittis: It is now enough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Elijah's ſatis eſt,</hi> may be reaſonably ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon theſe four Conſiderations; or in four re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects might he well ſay, <hi>It is now enough.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>In reſpect of what he had ſeen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>In reſpect of what he had ſuffered.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>In reſpect of what he had done.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>In reſpect of the years he had lived.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In all theſe reſpects, the Prophet might reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſay, <hi>Nunc ſatis est, It is now enough;</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, <hi>Lord I have ſeen enough to make me weary of this World; And I have ſuffered enough to make me weary of my Life: And I have done enough in the faithfull diſcharge of my duty in the Office of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, whereunto I was called: And I have lived long enough, even to deſire to live no longer in this wretched World; therefore now Lord, I beſeech yee diſmiſs me, Lord take away my Soule.</hi> So here are four <hi>enoughs,</hi> and they are all grounded in the 14. <hi>verſe</hi> of this <hi>Chapter,</hi> and in this <hi>Text.</hi> For firſt, He complains there, <hi>The Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>have forſaken thy Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, broke down thine Altars, and Slaine thy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets with the Sword:</hi> There's his <hi>Satis Vidi, I have ſeen enough.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:59533:4"/>
            <p> Secondly, He complains, <hi>That he onely is left, and they ſeek his Life to take it away:</hi> There's his <hi>Satis Tuli, I have ſuffered enough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>I have been Zealous for the Lord God of Hosts:</hi> There's his <hi>Satis Feci, I have done enough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Thoſe three things before mentioned, which he had <hi>Seen,</hi> which he had <hi>Suffered,</hi> and which he had <hi>Done,</hi> were not the worke of a ſhort time; they were the worke of many years; he was now grown old under his ſufferings, and doing his Duty, and ſo willing to follow the Generation of his Fathers, <hi>For I am no better then my Fathers:</hi> There's his <hi>Satis Vixi.</hi> And in all theſe reſpects he concludes, <hi>It is now enough,</hi> and begs for a diſmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Lord take away my Soule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To all theſe <hi>enoughs,</hi> we ſhall ſpeak ſomething briefly, with the inferences from them: And firſt of his <hi>Satis Vidi, I have ſeen enough:</hi> That is, (as himſelf Interprets himſelf, <hi>ver.</hi> 14.) of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, irreligion, profaneneſs, and Idolatry of the times and places that he lived in, to make him weary of the world, and of his life: And that is the firſt ground of this his requeſt to Almighty God, to take away his Soule.</p>
            <p>The inference from hence is this:</p>
            <p>That to live in evill times and places where
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59533:5"/>iniquity doth abound, is to pious Souls, and to ſuch as fear God, matter of great griefe and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of heart, even enough to make them weary, not onely of thoſe times and places, but even of their Lives too. St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us of <hi>Lot</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in <hi>Sodom, That his righteous Soule was vext from day to day with their unlawfull doings,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.7.8. The holy Prophet <hi>David</hi> complains in this caſe, and bewails his hard condition in this reſpect, even in paſſionate expreſſions, <hi>Woe is me that I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to dwell in</hi> Meſech, <hi>and to have my habitation among the Tents of</hi> Kedar. And the Prophet <hi>Habak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kuk,</hi> as paſſionately as he, in the ſame caſe, <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.2, 3, 4. <hi>O Lord, how long ſhall I cry, and thou wilt not heare! yea, even cry out of violence, and thou wilt not help? Why doſt thou ſhew me iniquity, and cauſe me to behold ſorrow? for the Law is diſſolved, and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth not goe forth: the wicked doth compaſs about the righteous: therefore unjuſt judgement doth proceed.</hi> Thus we ſee how righteous ſouls are affected in theſe caſes, and afflicted with grief and ſorrow un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſence of the wickedneſſes, &amp; abominations that are committed under the Sunne, in the times and places where they live. <hi>Reaſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe hereby God is diſhonoured, whoſe glory is dear unto them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:59533:5"/> 2. The Church is ſcandalized, holy Religion reproached, the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt aſperſed, and the way of God evill ſpoken of, eſpecially if theſe things be done, and ſuffered in a Chriſtian Church, or Common-wealth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It gives ſo great offence to many weak ones, that it cauſes them to with-draw themſelves from the ſociety of the faithfull, to abhorre the Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of the Lord, to deſpiſe the ſtanding Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Church, and for thoſe evills, which we ſee, to forſake that which is good, to throw up all, and to make ſeparation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Hereby they deſtroy their own ſouls, of which others fearing God, are more ſenſible then they themſelves: Chriſt beholding <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and fore-ſeeing the calamity that hung over it, <hi>Wept for it,</hi> they did not ſo for themſelves.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They provoke wrath, and draw down judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon the place where they live, both upon themſelves and others for their ſakes: <hi>For theſe things ſakes comes the wrath of God upon the Children of diſobedience,</hi> Epheſ. 5.6.</p>
            <p>Upon theſe Conſiderations, pious ſouls, men fearing God, are ſenſible of the ſins of others, as well as of their own; and of the iniquity of the times and places where they live, and they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59533:6"/>to them matter of great ſorrow and greif of heart: <hi>I beheld the tranſgreſſors, and was greived,</hi> Pſal. 119.158.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It ſhould teach men wiſedom, where they can, and as farr as they can, to uſe prudence in the choyce of the places of their habitation, and when to make this one of their reſpects among all other, that they may ſeat themſelves in ſuch a place where the fear of God is amongſt them. <hi>Lot</hi> made but an ill choyce (though he lighted on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Land) when he choſe the plain of <hi>Sodom</hi> to pitch his Tent in: <hi>Abraham</hi> might well be afraid to ſojourne in <hi>Gerar,</hi> when he perceived <hi>the feare of God was not in that place,</hi> Gen. 20.11. When we match our Sons, or Daughters, we enquire dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, what Portion, what Parentage, we enquire after the fatneſs of the Land, fruitfulneſs of the Soyle, convenience of ſituation, and the like, and all this with good diſcretion too; but among all the reſt, we ſhould not leave out this as a maine conſideration, whether we diſpoſe of them to ſuch a place where the fear of God is among the people the Inhabitants there, whether they live under a good Miniſtery, a good Majeſtracy, a good Government, where wickedneſs and vice is puniſhed, were Religion and godlineſs is ſet up,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59533:6"/>countenanc't, and encouraged, whether the feare of God be in the place? a very conſiderable bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and a great part of their happineſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Try your zeale and love to God and his truth to holy Religion, and the Goſpel by this Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, by your hatred of ſin, as well in others, as in your ſelves, and by your grief and ſorrow of heart, when you ſee it reign and abound in the Land, and in the times and places where you live. Beloved, we live in evill times, and in places bad enough, where you have occaſion enough given you to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe your zeale, and to ſhew your love, and grief, and anger, if you have any in this caſe, you may ſee as our Prophet did, the Law forſaken, the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant broken, the Worſhip of God neglected, the Ordinances deſpiſed, the Sabbath prophan'd, the Sacraments ſlighted, &amp;c. if we can ſee theſe things, and not be ſenſible of them, and ſorry for them, at leaſt where we cannot help them, ſurely our zeale is cold, and our love but ſmall; <hi>Set a Marke</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>upon the Foreheads of all thoſe that Mourne for the aboninations that are done in the City, Ezek.</hi> 9.4. 'Tis an Argument of a gracious heart, to take to heart the iniquities of the times, to ſigh and mourn for them, to be diſpleaſed with them, and troubled at them.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:59533:7"/> 3. Here's an object and opportunity for ſuch as are in place and power, to exerciſe their authority in ſuppreſſing ſin, in puniſhing the wickedneſs of the times and places where they live, in ſtopping the courſe and current of iniquity prevailing: If Magiſtrates, they muſt be cloathed with zeale as with a cloak, they muſt put on Juſtice as a Robe, and Judgement as a Crown or Diadem, they muſt be girt about with the Sword of vengeance, and let proud and inſolent offenders know, they doe not beare that Sword in vain: If Miniſters, they muſt cry aloud, and not ſpare, and never leave crying out againſt the prevailing and reigning ſins of the times and places where they live, till they have cryed them down, and take heed they doe not by their ſilence and connivence, make themſelves partakers of other mens ſins: Parents of Children, Maſters of ſamilies, they are in thoſe leſſer <hi>ſocieties</hi> which they are ſet to Govern; both Kings, Prieſts, and Prophets, all which Offices they muſt execute in the Government of their little Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, every one in the ſeverall Sphere wherein he moves, and Calling wherein he is ſet, according to his place and power is to endeavour the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of ſin, the puniſhment of wickedneſs, and the maintenance and encouragement of true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and vertue.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:59533:7"/> 4. Here's occaſion and opportunity (in ſuch evill times as here we ſpeak of) for the Saints and ſervants of the moſt high, the favourites of Heaven, to ſtand up, and to ſhew themſelves, to make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for the People, and Places where they are, for the diverting of thoſe Judgements which theſe ſins call for, to uſe the Intereſt which they have in God, to intreat for the reſt, that God would ſpare them, to ſtand in the Gap (as <hi>Moſes</hi> did) to make Atonement for the People and Places where they are, as <hi>Aaron</hi> did, to divert, ſtay, ſuſpend, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move Judgement denounc't againſt them, when wrath is gone forth, and the Plague begun; and happy thoſe Places which have ſuch as theſe are in them, though but a few favourites of Heaven, to make in to God, to uſe their intereſt in him, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat for the reſt, great things hath God done at their requeſt in the behalfe of others, and even thoſe that deſpiſe them, are more beholden to them then they are aware of.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In ſuch evill times and places as we ſpeak of, we are to be admoniſhed to walk warily for fear of Infection, for fear of ſeduction, leaſt we come to be corrupted and infected by them, and ſo while we complain the times are evill, we our ſelves make them worſe; ſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> argues, <hi>Ephe.</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:59533:8"/>5.15. <hi>Walk circumſpectly, becauſe the dayes are evil;</hi> By no means to have any <hi>fellowſhip with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull works of darkneſs, but rather reprove them, (Epheſ.</hi> 5.11.) to ſhew our diſlike of them by avoyding them, to reprove them by a ſober, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and godly converſation, the moſt reall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe to the lewd and looſe carriage and behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of wicked men that can be; by this oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the holy converſation of godly men becomes more illuſtrious; thus doth their light come to <hi>ſhine before Men,</hi> ſo that <hi>they ſeeing their good works,</hi> are moved to glorifie the <hi>Father which is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> this is to walk as Children of the light, and to ſhine as lights in the midſt of a froward, and a dark Generation, which will be the great convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and condemnation of thoſe wicked men they live amongſt, and their own high prayſe and great reward another day: This was the high prayſe of <hi>Noah, Gen.</hi> 6.9. Noah <hi>was a juſt Man in his Generation:</hi> Why, what Generation was that? it was an evill Generation; <hi>When all Fleſh had cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted their wayes before the Lord,</hi> Noah <hi>ſtill kept his integrity, he was a juſt Man in his Generation.</hi> For <hi>Abraham</hi> in <hi>Caldea, Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodom, Job</hi> in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>z, Noah</hi> in his Generation to hold faſt his integrity, was their high prayſe.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:59533:8"/>
            <p> And ſo we have done with <hi>Elijah's</hi> firſt <hi>Satis eſt,</hi> the firſt of his <hi>enoughs, In reſpect of the evill he had ſeen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We come now to conſider of the ſecond, which <hi>reſpects the evill that he had Suffered, Satis Tuli, I have</hi> ſuffered <hi>enough;</hi> and this ariſeth out of thoſe words in the latter end of the 14. <hi>ver. They have Slain thy Prophets with the edge of the Sword, and I onely am left, and they ſeek my Life to take it away:</hi> By this, you may gather in what condition he was in reſpect of ſufferings, by Perſecution, Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Hunger, and Thirſt, and variety of dangers, threatning even Death it ſelf.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The inference from hence is this;</head>
               <p>That it is no news to ſee the beſt of Saints to ſuffer the worſt things that the world can doe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: To ſee <hi>Joſeph</hi> in the Priſon, <hi>Job</hi> upon the Dunghill, <hi>Jeremy</hi> in the Dungeon, <hi>Jonah</hi> in the Whales belly, <hi>Iſay</hi> under the Saw, <hi>Paul</hi> under the Axe, <hi>Stephen</hi> under a ſtorme of Stones, and all this under the hands of wicked men; and more then this, when ſuch wicked and ungodly men live at eaſe, and in peace, proſper, and flouriſh, <hi>Come in no misfortune like other men; neither are they plagned like other men,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.5. Theſe things may ſeem ſtrange
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59533:9"/>to humane apprehenſion, and doe; but they are no news to thoſe that are well read in the wayes of Providence, nor ſtrange neither, when wiſely weighed, and rightly conſidered: And to help you in thoſe Conſiderations, I commend you to two of <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalmes, the 37. and the 73. both ſpent wholly upon this ſubject, to take away the ſcandall of the Croſſe; In both which, he firſt rayſes the Objections, and then brings in full an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to them for the clearing of Gods Juſtice in this croſs diſpenſation of Providence, and for the ſatisfying of himſelf and others in this matter: I ſhall therefore wave what the Prophet hath there delivered, and onely ſhew you very briefly ſome Reaſons why and how it comes ſo to paſſe, and what profitable Uſe we may make of this Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and ſo paſſe on to the next.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reaſons.</head>
               <p>If you aske me then, How it comes to paſs that the beſt men ſhould ſuffer the worſt things here in this world? I Anſwer:</p>
               <p n="1">1. This proceeds from the malice of <hi>Satan,</hi> ever contriving miſchief againſt the Church, even to the utter ruine of it, if it were poſſible, that the gates of Hell ſhould prevail againſt it; There is
<pb facs="tcp:59533:9"/>an enmity between the Woman and the Serpent, which will never be reconciled.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From the hatred that wicked men (well nigh as bad as himſelfe) bear againſt it; his very Inſtruments and Agents are ready to execute his will upon it; the enmity is not onely between the Woman and the Serpent, but between their Seed alſo: Wicked men are the very Seed of the Serpent, and doe as naturally maligne and hate the Church, and Children of God, as the Serpent doth a man.</p>
               <p n="3">3. From their own folly, which by ſinne lay themſelves open to their malice: <hi>Balaam</hi> knew he could have no power over the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to hurt them, except he could deviſe ſome way how to draw them to ſin againſt God. But when he had contriv'd a way to make them commit <hi>Fornication with the Daughters of</hi> Moab, he knew he had his purpoſe on them in expoſing them to wrath and judgement, <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This comes to paſs by the juſt and wiſe Providence of God, not onely permitting, but or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering it ſo, for holy ends, and good purpoſes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For tryall of their Faith, that they may come out of them as Gold refined.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For exerciſe of their Graces, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t probentur,
<pb facs="tcp:59533:10"/>approbentur, improbentur;</hi> that they may be proved, approved, improved.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For purging out and mortifying of their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, crucifying of their luſts, and inordinate affections.</p>
               <p n="4">4. For holding of them cloſe to Duty, as of Repentance, Prayer, and a conſtant dependance upon God.</p>
               <p n="5">5. For the weyning of them from this preſent evill world, that they might ſeek and affect better things in a better world, <hi>and minde the things that are above,</hi> Coloſ. 3.1.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That they may have nothing to ſuffer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, they are chaſtiſed in the world, that they may not be condemned with the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Are theſe the ends why God ſuffereth his Saints to ſuffer? Then wellcome ſufferings by the grace of God; Wellcome Afflictions by the will of God, they ſhall be a benefit unto us, a greater advantage then the Eaſe, Peace, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of wicked men can be unto them; nay, then theſe could have been unto our ſelves, if we had had them: <hi>Eaſe ſlayeth the fooliſh, and the proſperity of Fooles deſtroyeth them,</hi> Prov. 1.32. Standing Pooles gather mud and dirt, when run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59533:10"/>Streames keep pure and clear; Winde and Thunder purge the Ayre, and the Fire doth not conſume, but refine the Gold that is caſt into it: and ſuch are the ſufferings of the Saints &amp; ſervants of God to thoſe that are exerciſed under them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Think not ſtrange of thoſe fiery tryalls, and that the beſt men are ſo often under them, it were ſtrange if it were not ſo; <hi>Chriſtianus Crucianus,</hi> the Croſſe is the Chriſtians badge, the Cogniſance of a Diſciple, our Lord himſelf the Captain of our ſalvation, was made perfect through ſufferings, he carried the Croſs upon his own ſhoulders up Mount <hi>Calvary,</hi> upon which himſelf was Crucified; and we may not think much that come after him, with <hi>Symon</hi> the <hi>Cyrenian</hi> to carry one end of it: Shew me the man of any ſtanding in the profeſſion of Chriſtianity, that hath been conſtantly free from ſufferings, and I will ſay, <hi>He is either a Miracle, or a Monſter in Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Think not the worſe neither of your ſelves, nor others in this caſe; Croſſes are not Curſes, nor the greateſt Sufferers (therefore) the greateſt Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: The ſufferings of the Saints are ſo farr from being Arguments of Gods diſpleaſure towards them; that clean contrary, they are rather evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of his love and favour: So St. <hi>Paul</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59533:11"/>
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.6. <hi>Whom he loveth he chaſteneth, and correcteth every ſonne whom he receiveth.</hi> St. <hi>Jerom</hi> never feared his eſtate worſe, then when for three years together he lived in peace, and was free from all trouble and adverſity. If thou faint in the time of adverſity, thy ſtrength is ſmall: Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, all promiſes of bleſſings and good things made to Gods Children, are made with exception of the Croſs, againſt which, even grace and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, piety and obedience, holineſs it ſelf is no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection: Sanctity and ſuffering may ſtand toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. They were holy ones of whom God ſpake, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 89.32.33. <hi>Their iniquity will I viſit with the rod, and their ſins with ſcourges: but my loving kindneſs will I never take from them, nor ſuffer my truth to faile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Beware of murmuring, by no means ſuffer your hearts to break out in any evill thoughts againſt God and his Providence, even in his moſt ſevere proceedings againſt you, as if he dealt too hardly with you, this were to charge God fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; <hi>But let him be ever juſtified in his ſayings</hi> and doings, <hi>and clear when he is judged;</hi> and to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence all clamour, murmurings, and mutinous thoughts. In this caſe take with you theſe two conſiderations. Firſt, See ſin in all, let the means
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59533:11"/>by which you ſuffer be what it will, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of it what they can, doe but look well into it, and you ſhall finde, <hi>Sinne</hi> lyes at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome: <hi>David</hi> ſaw this, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.18. <hi>Look upon my adverſity and my trouble, and forgive me all my Sinne. Jeremy</hi> ſaw it in his <hi>Lamentations, cap.</hi> 3.39. <hi>Why doth living man complaine, man ſuffering for his Sinnes?</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, <hi>There is no reaſon for it, let him conſider well of it, and he ſhall find, his Sinnes are greater then his ſufferings, his ſufferings leſs then his deſervings.</hi> Secondly, See God in all, though ſin be the cauſe of all, 'tis God that is the Judge of all: <hi>Is there any evill in the City, and the Lord hath not done it?</hi> And if it be the Lord, let him doe what he will, he neither can, nor will doe unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? When <hi>Moſes</hi> told <hi>Aaron</hi> in a grievous Affliction that befell him, <hi>Levit.</hi> 10. <hi>That it was from the Lord;</hi> The Text ſayes, <hi>Aaron held his peace, ver.</hi> 3. he had no more to ſay. <hi>If it be the Lords doing, let him doe what is good in his eyes; his will be done at well upon us, as by us, and as well in taking away, as giving:</hi> Ever ſay with holy <hi>Job</hi> in the like caſe, <hi>Bleſſed be the Name of the Lord,</hi> Job 1.22.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In the ſufferings of the Saints and ſervan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of God here in this world, let wicked and ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men reade their own doome, and certainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59533:12"/>That they have a heavy reckoning to make to God in the day of account, that great is the wrath of the Allmighty againſt them, and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full the Judgements that doe await them. <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>I viſit the City upon which my name is called, and doe you think to eſcape? you ſhall not eſcape. And if the righteous be ſcarely ſaved, where ſhall the ungodly and the Sinner appeare?</hi> Surely if he doe ſo ſeverely ſcourge his own Children with Scourges, he will torment them with Scorpions. <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerved in his time, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.11. That <hi>becauſe Judgement was not ſpeedily executed upon evill doers; therefore the hearts of the ſonnes of men were wholly ſet upon wickedneſs.</hi> But there is no reaſon for it, if they knew all; alas! they ſee not that their day is comming, they may make a Covenant with the Grave, and with Hell be at agreement, but that Covenant will not ſtand; they may cry, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ace, peace unto themſelves, where there is no peace,</hi> and ſo ſleep a while in their ſecurity, but their damnation ſleepeth not; they may ſing Requiems to their ſouls, <hi>Ede, bibe, lude,</hi> Eat, drink, and be merry, but they ſee not the hand-writing on the Wall, <hi>Mene, Mene, &amp;c. Thou art weighed in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, and art found too light:</hi> they heare not the dreadfull noyſe, <hi>Stulte hac nocte, This night ſhall they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59533:12"/>fetch away thy ſoule.</hi> With what deriſion doth the wiſedom of God ſpeak to ſuch, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.9. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, O young man, in thy youth, and let thy heart cheere thee in the dayes of thy youth, and walk in the ſight of thine eyes, and the wayes of thine heart; but remember, that for all theſe things God will bring thee into judgement.</hi> But the Lord ſpeaks terror to them by his royall Prophet <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 50.21. <hi>Thus and thus haſt thou done, and I held my tongue, and thou thoughteſt me ſuch a one as thy ſelfe: but I will reprove thee, and ſet thy ſinnes in order before thee.</hi> Beloved, take this for a moſt certaine obſervation, 'Tis the moſt dangerous ſtate in the world for a man to goe on in ſinne, and proſper, to live in ſinne, and to live at eaſe, free from adverſity and affliction: <hi>Ephraim is given unto Idols: let him alone,</hi> ſaith the Lord by the Prophet <hi>Hoſea, c.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Nolo istam miſericordiam,</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Jerom) Lord let me have none of that mercy, to be let alone in my ſinne: Scinde, ure, ſeca ut in aeternum parcas:</hi> Let me ſuffer any thing in this life that thou ſhalt pleaſe to lay upon me, that I may be ſpared in the life to come, and have nothing to ſuffer in the other world. Let all ſecure ſinners know, There is a Pit digging up for them, a very ſignificant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Prophet, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.13. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntill the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59533:13"/>Pit be digged for the ungodly:</hi> Now the longer the Pit is in digging, the deeper it will be; and the deeper it is, the greater will be the fall into it, and the more impoſſible the recovery out of it, and ſo deep it may be, that it may let the ſinner down into Hell it ſelf. I conclude this Point with that Advertiſement of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> which he gives to all ſuch ſecure ſinners, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Know ye not that the patience and long ſuffering of God ſhould leade to Repentance? But thou out of thine hardneſs, and heart that cannot repent, treaſureſt up unto thy ſelfe wrath against the day of wrath, and the declaration of the righteous judgement of God.</hi> And what a miſerable thing is this, for a man to treaſure up unto himſelf wrath againſt the day of wrath, and all his dayes to be carrying fuell to that fire in which himſelfe is eternally to burne?</p>
               <p>Laſtly, From this truth, let all men certainly conclude a Judge to come; for he that is the Judge of all the world hath ſaid it, <hi>That he will render to every man according to his works,</hi> Rom. 2.6. But we ſee, that is not done in this life; in this life here are croſs diſpenſations of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, by which it falls out oft times clean con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerved this in his time, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.14. <hi>That there be righteous Men to whom it cometh
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59533:13"/>according to the working of the wicked: and there be wicked Men to whom it cometh according to the work of the righteous.</hi> The royall Prophet <hi>David</hi> before him obſerved the ſame, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſal.</hi> 73. and complineth of it, <hi>That the wicked flouriſh, when the righteous periſh; they live at eaſe, and have all things that their hearts can wiſh:</hi> When the righteous are under the Croſs, and under the Rod, chaſtiſed every Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and viſited every moment, <hi>Hic pietatis honos?</hi> Is this the reward of piety? Is this to render to every man according to his works? ſurely no, and if things ſhould reſt thus, then well might Saint <hi>Paul</hi> complain, <hi>That of all men, the Saints and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God were moſt miſerable: If in this life onely we have hope, then are we of all men moſt miſerable:</hi> But ſay not ſo, and think not ſo, but poſſeſſe your ſouls with patience for a time, and mark the end, and you ſhall finde, it is not ſo. Remember that of St. <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 17.31. <hi>That God hath appointed a day wherein to Judge the world in righteouſneſs, by his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> when he will make all theſe croſſe reckonings right and ſtreight, wherein he will render tribulation to them that have troubled his, and to thoſe that have been troubled, reſt with him; when he will ſay to all thoſe ſecure and ſenſuall ſinners, (as to the rich Epicure in the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59533:14"/>Goſpel,) <hi>Sonnes, remember you in your life time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived pleaſure, and theſe my ſervants received pain: now they are comforted, and you are tormented:</hi> that's the day wherein this word ſhall be made good, <hi>That he will render to every Man according to his works,</hi> therefore called, <hi>The day of refreſhing,</hi> Acts 3.19. <hi>The day of reſtauration: The day of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous judgement of God,</hi> Rom. 2.5. Gods Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are alwayes righteous, but they are not alwayes declared to be ſo: but then they ſhall be declared to be ſo, in the ſight of all the world, men, and Angels, and they ſhall all confeſſe and ſay, as in the Pſalme, <hi>Verely there is a reward for the righteous: doubtleſs there is a God that judgeth the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo we have done with the Prophets ſecond <hi>Satis est,</hi> the ſecond of his <hi>enoughs</hi> ſpoken in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to what he had ſuffered, <hi>Satis Tuli, I have ſuffered enough.</hi> We now paſs to the third, ſpoken in reference to what he <hi>had done.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Satis Feci, I have done enough:</hi> And this ariſeth out of the firſt words of the 14. <hi>verſe, I have been very jealous, or zealous, for the Lord God of Hosts:</hi> this word is very ſignificant and comprehenſive, it containes in it much; as the faithfull diſcharge of his duty in the Office of a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59533:14"/>Prophet whereunto he was called, his care to maintaine the true Religion and Worſhip of God, his courage in reproving the ſinnes of the ten Tribes, even in the greateſt, <hi>Ahab</hi> himſelfe not excepted; his zeale in convincing and ſilencing the Prieſts of <hi>Baall</hi> in thoſe perillous times, when they had the protection and countenance of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority on their ſides, and much more; and that he did not theſe things coldly, negligently, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functorily; but with all earneſtneſs and fervency, (as the word imports) for it comes from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to hiſſe, as Iron doth, when being red hot it is dipt in Water, ſuch was his activity in the performance of theſe his duties, and fervency of affection: <hi>Quicquid egit, valide egit,</hi> as the <hi>Italians</hi> are ſaid to doe, <hi>The zeale of Gods Houſe did even conſume him,</hi> as another Prophet ſpeaks: he did theſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with zeale as hot as fire: neither in this te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony did he arrogate to himſelfe any thing at all more then due, nor commend himſelfe above his meaſure, the Story of his Life and Actions evidently declares the truth of what he here aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, <hi>That he had been very zealous for the Lord God of Hoſts, in doing his Will, in ſeeking his Glory, and in upholding and maintaining his true Worſhip againſt all oppoſers, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:59533:15"/>
               <p> The Inferences from hence are theſe three.</p>
               <p>The firſt, Thoſe that are for God, muſt doe the will of God.</p>
               <p>The ſecond, It is not enough to doe, <hi>Oper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> operato;</hi> but they muſt doe it as they ſhould be done, in due manner, with due affections, and they muſt doe it home, or els it will never reach to <hi>Elijah's Satis eſt, It is enough.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third, It ſhall be their greateſt comfort in the evill day, that they have done ſo: the illa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe is cleare out of <hi>Elijah</hi>'s <hi>Satis est</hi> in the Text, compar'd with the firſt words of the 14. <hi>v.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, Thoſe that are for God, muſt doe the will of God in that Place, Calling, and Condition of Life wherein God hath ſet them: They muſt doe his will, whether it be Prophet, or Apoſtle, or a common Chriſtian, Magiſtrate, or Miniſter, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Beleever, every one muſt in his Place, doe the will of God: It is our dayly Prayer, <hi>That his will may be done in Earth, as it is in Heaven:</hi> And in this Prayer, Is it fit that we ſhould over-look our ſelves? No, as it is our dayly Prayer, ſo it ſhould be our dayly practiſe to doe his will: <hi>Not every one that ſaith unto me,</hi> Lord, Lord, <hi>ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, but he that doth the will of my Father which is in Heaven. Not the hearers, but
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59533:15"/>the doers of the Law ſhall be juſtified: If you know theſe things, bleſſed are you if you doe them.</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity calls for Action; it is not Logicall, but Morall; not ſpeculative, but practique: it conſiſts not in ſaying, nor in knowing, nor in profeſſing, but in working; there muſt be a <hi>Feci</hi> in it: <hi>Regnum Dei non datur otioſis,</hi> (as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeaks) the Kingdom of God is not given to idle profeſſors, and pretenders; the Calling of a Chriſtian is a laborious Calling, a Building, a Husbandry, a Warfare, all theſe call to work, there is ſomthing to be done whereby we may bring glory to God, good to men, and comfort to our own ſouls: The very Heathen were ſenſible of this, That they were bound to doe ſome good in the Generation wherein they lived; and they that did not ſo, they were reproach't, as <hi>In utile pondus terrae,</hi> an unprofitable burden to the Earth. <hi>Fruges con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumere nati:</hi> as if they were borne onely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure the good things of the Earth. He was an honeſt Moraliſt that ſpake it, <hi>Mortem non timore, quia ita vixi, ut fruſtra me natum non exiſtimem;</hi> I am not afraid to dye, becauſe I have ſo lived, as that no man may think that I was born in vaine: a teſtimony that may ſhame many Chriſtians that ſo live and dye as if they were born in vain, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59533:16"/>burdens to the Earth: Terrible is the doome of the unprofitable ſervant in the Goſpel, <hi>Take the unprofitable ſervant, binde him hand and foot, and caſt him into utter darkneſs:</hi> He doth not charge him as being an hurtfull ſervant, but as an unprofitable ſervant; not with waſting his <hi>Talent,</hi> but with not improving it. Beloved, God looks we ſhould be profitable ſervants, that we ſhould bring glory to his name, honour to the Goſpel, and that we ſhould doe good in our Generation, that the world ſhould be the better for our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into it, not the worſe: Can any man ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, or can it ſtand with reaſon to think, That the moſt holy God, and wiſe Creator of all things, ſhould Create ſuch a Creature as Man is for nought, and not look for ſervice from him, and glory out of him? Why there is no Creature that he hath made, though never ſo mean and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, but he looks for glory by it, and ſervice out of it, in it's kind; <hi>Natura nihil facit fruſtra,</hi> The God of Nature hath made nothing in vain: And ſhall Man, the moſt excellent piece of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (next unto the Angels) be unſerviceable, and bring in nothing to the glory of the Creator? Man, endued with ſuch rare gifts and abilities to doe good withall, both to himſelf and others,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59533:16"/>Did the Creator endue him with ſuch rare excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies above the reſt of the Creatures, ſuch as Underſtanding, Will, Memory, Affections, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Judgement, Knowledge, Conſcience, for nought? No ſurely, To whom much is given, of him much will be required: great receipts will make men liable to great accounts: A time will come when they ſhall give an account both of their Time, and of their Talents, how they have uſed and improved them, what good they have done with them. Beloved, That man ſhall never dye comfortably, which hath not in his life time, in ſome ſort, anſwered the end of his Creation; The end of his Creation is, to glorifie God, to doe good to men in his Generation, and to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſalvation of his own ſoule: <hi>Bleſſed is that ſervant whom when his Maſter cometh, he ſhall finde ſo doing.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes.</head>
               <p n="1">1. It reproves all carnall, careleſs, and ſecure Chriſtians, if I may call them ſuch, and not rather Epicure, or Atheiſt, that make no Conſcience at all of doing good; ſure they think ſalvation will come of courſe, and God will drop down happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into their laps, while they ſit ſtill, and never look after it: What ſhall we eat, or what ſhall we drink, or where withall ſhall we be cloathed, are
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59533:17"/>the things that take up their care and thoughts? but the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num neceſſarium,</hi> that one thing that is neceſſary, wholly layd aſide: Surely a great part of the world are very Atheiſts, they either think there's no heaven at all, or they are much miſtaken in the way to it, and the means of attaining it; We muſt work, walk, runne, fight the good fight of Faith; Strive to enter in at the ſtreight gate: through many tribulations, many ſufferings, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cumbatings; there are corruptions to be mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, Luſts to be crucified, Temptations to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, afflictions to be ſuffered, ſpirituall wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to be wraſtled withall: <hi>Qui cupit optatam curſu contingere metam, multa tulit fuitq pius ſudovit &amp; alſit:</hi> Chriſtianity is no idle Calling, it will take up the whole man, and the whole time, it will keep us doing in the practiſe of all Chriſtian duties, and the exerciſe of all Chriſtian graces.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This reproves the <hi>Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pticks</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>noſticks</hi> of theſe times, whoſe Religion lyes all in their Braine, and in their Tongue, the Practique part of Chriſtianity they lay by, and place it all in Theory and ſpeculation, they have found out a neerer way to Heaven then ever our Fathers knew, an eaſier, and a cheaper, they can talk themſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lves thither, and diſpute themſelves thither, and all
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59533:17"/>this while ſit ſtill, and neither work, nor walk for it at all; the good works which Chriſtianity calls for, they pay with good words; their devotion is turn'd into diſputing, their faith into faction, and their charity into contention; the mayne of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion they place in hearing of Sermons. <hi>Pliny</hi> writes of a certain Serpent, <hi>Aure concepit, Ore parit,</hi> That it conceives in the Eare, and brings forth at the Mouth: as fit an Embleme for ſuch profeſſors as can be: They conceive by the Eare, in an inſatiable deſire of Hearing; and bring forth at the Mouth, by endleſs diſputing, and diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. But as to the Hand by working, or the Foot by walking, their Religion reacheth not, without which, all the reſt is but vain, as St. <hi>James</hi> tells us. Therefore, <hi>Set me as a Seale upon thine heart, and as a Bracelet upon thine Arme,</hi> ſaith the Church to Chriſt, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6. Upon which, St. <hi>Bernard</hi> thus Gloſſeth, <hi>In corde ſunt cogitationes, in brachiis ſunt operationes, ergo ſuper cor, &amp; ſuper brachium:</hi> The heart is the ſeat of affections, the Arme the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of actions: Set me therefore as a Seale upon thy heart, and as a bracelet upon thine arme, that with the one I may ever affect, and with the other effect the things that pleaſe thee. Beloved, Not onely the Law, but the Goſpel, every where
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59533:18"/>calls for good works at our hands: <hi>Be zealous of good works, Titus</hi> 2.14. <hi>Fruitfull in good works,</hi> Col. 1.10. <hi>And let ours alſo learn to ſhew forth good works:</hi> What? though they be not <hi>Cauſa Regnandi,</hi> The cauſe why we ſhall reigne; yet they are, <hi>Via Regni,</hi> The way to the Kingdome, and the way which God hath appointed we ſhould walk in thither: What though they doe not ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie, nor merit? yet they are profitable for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary uſes: By them is our Heavenly Father glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt honoured and adored; they are evidences of the ſoundneſs of our Faith, the ſincerity of our profeſſion; they bring comfort to the Conſcience here, and there is a certain reward for them in Heaven; though not, <hi>Propter opera;</hi> yet <hi>Secundum opera,</hi> according to our works to be given unto us. <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which dye in the Lord, even ſo ſaith the ſpirit, for they reſt from their labours, and their works fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them:</hi> And happy is he which hath ſtore of them in that day to prayſe him in the gates.</p>
               <p>And thus much of the firſt inference, drawn from <hi>Elijah</hi>'s third <hi>Satis eſt,</hi> that is, <hi>I have done enough:</hi> Thoſe that are for God, muſt doe the will of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond follows, and 'tis this, That it is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59533:18"/>not enough to doe the will of God, <hi>Opere operato:</hi> but they muſt doe it as it ſhould be done, or els it will never reach to the <hi>Satis eſt</hi> in the Text: Now this <hi>Satis: eſt,</hi> hath reſpect to two things in doing the will of God. Firſt, The manner of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it. Secondly, The extent of it. The firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, that it be done well. The ſecond, that it be done home, they both are included in the Word <hi>Zealous: I have been Zealous for the Lord God of Hoſts.</hi> Zeale is a vehement affection, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of Love and Anger, and Actions flowing from theſe two, are ever done in earneſt, they are done home and throughly, and ſo ought we to doe all things that we doe for God: The <hi>Opus operatum,</hi> the work done will not ſerve the turne, but it muſt be rightly qualified in all the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of it, and done in a right manner: If we love the Lord our God, we muſt love him with all our heart, with all our ſoule, with all our mind, and with all our ſtrength: If we ſerve him, we muſt ſerve him with reverence and godly ſeare: If we worſhip him, we muſt worſhip him in <hi>Spirit,</hi> and in <hi>Truth Luther</hi> ſaid well, <hi>That God loves Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, rather then Verbs,</hi> the manner of doing, more then the work done, the will more then the deed, the mind more then the matter, we muſt not ſerve
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59533:19"/>God negligently, nor we muſt not ſerve him by halves, either of theſe make our obedience fall ſhort of <hi>Elijah</hi>'s <hi>Satis eſt</hi> in the Text: To ſay, we beleeve in God, we love God, and we feare God, and not to obey him, to ſhew our faith by our works, and our fear by our worſhip, <hi>Non ſatis eſt,</hi> it is not enough; but to our faith to joyne our obedience, and to our fear to joyne our worſhip, and to our love our care to keep his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>Satis eſt,</hi> it is enough: To profeſs that we know God, to confeſs his Name, to draw neer unto him with our lips, and in all outward de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment to have a forme of godlineſs, <hi>Non ſatis eſt,</hi> it is not enough; but to know God in Chriſt, reconciling the world unto himſelfe, to draw neer unto him with our hearts, and deareſt affections, and with the forme of godlineſs to ſhew forth the power of it, <hi>Satis est,</hi> it is enough: To cry <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> as in the Goſpel, and <hi>Templum Domini, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum Domini, The Temple of the Lord, The Temple of the Lord,</hi> as the <hi>Jews</hi> did in <hi>Jeremy, Non ſatis eſt,</hi> it is not enough: but to doe the will of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in Heaven, and in his Temple to ſpeak of his Honour, and to worſhip him aright, <hi>Satis est,</hi> it is enough. To make our boaſt of God, and of his Law, to heare every day a Sermon, to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59533:19"/>know the Miſtery of the Goſpel, to have a mouth full of Scripture ready at all times to throw at an adverſary in diſpute or diſcourſe, <hi>Non ſatis est,</hi> it is not enough: but to know the truth as it is in <hi>Jeſus,</hi> to receive the truth with the love of the truth, to anſwer the end of the Evangelicall Law, which is Love out of a pure heart a good Conſcience, and Faith unfeigned, <hi>Satis est,</hi> it is enough. To bring multitudes of ſacrifices and oblations unto the Lord, to ſtretch out our hands before him, and to make many Prayers, <hi>Non ſatis eſt,</hi> it is not enough: but to waſh us, to make us cleane, to take away the evill of our works from before his eyes, to ceaſe to doe evill, and learne to doe well, <hi>Satis est,</hi> it is enough. To come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord <hi>with thouſands of Rams, and ten thouſand Rivers of Oyle, to give the fruit of my body for the ſin of my ſoule,</hi> (Micha 6.6.7.) <hi>Non ſatis est,</hi> it is not enough: but <hi>to doe Judgement, to love Mercy, and to walk humbly before the Lord, Satis est,</hi> it is enough. To conclude this point, to be admitted into the viſible Church, to be matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated into it by Baptiſme, to live in a profeſſed ſubjection to the Goſpel of Chriſt, to come to Church, to heare Sermons, to ſit out the Service, and at the appointed times to receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59533:20"/>of the Lords Supper, (though this be more then we can gaine of many among you,) <hi>Non ſatis est,</hi> it is not enough: but to make it our care all the dayes of our life, to make good the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which we made in our Baptiſme, to become Members of the inviſible Church, incorporated into it, and united unto it by the bonds of faith and of the ſpirit, to expreſs the power of the Word, Sacraments, and Spirit working by them in a conſtant holy walking before the Lord, as becomes the Members of that holy Society, <hi>Satis est,</hi> it is enough: And ſo we have made good the ſecond Inference drawn out of <hi>Elijah's</hi> third <hi>Satis est,</hi> in reference to what he had done, <hi>Satis Feci, I have done enough.</hi> But ſtay a little, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we take our leave of this <hi>Satis est,</hi> it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary we ſhould anſwer an Objection that lyes in our way, and muſt be removed before we can proceed any further.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj. Quid audio?</hi> What is that I heare? <hi>Satis feci, I have done enough:</hi> Who can ſay ſo? be he a Prophet, be he an Apoſtle, an Evangeliſt, be he the holieſt of Saints that ever lived, can he ſay of himſelfe, <hi>Satis feci, I have done enough?</hi> Is there a <hi>Satis</hi> in our obedience unto which we may arrive, and then ſay, <hi>It is enough?</hi> Our Saviour
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59533:20"/>tells us, <hi>That when we have done all that we can, we are unprofitable ſervants:</hi> How then can any ſay, <hi>It is enough?</hi> or <hi>I have done enough?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> To this I anſwer by a double diſtinction.</p>
               <p>Firſt thus, There is a <hi>Satis ad Juſtificationem;</hi> and there is a <hi>Satis ad Teſtificationem:</hi> there is a <hi>Satis</hi> as to Juſtification; and there is a <hi>Satis</hi> as to Teſtification. As to the former, there is no man can ſay, <hi>He hath done enough. Enter not into judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with thy ſervant, O Lord, for in thy ſight ſhall no man living be juſtified.</hi> Pſal. 143.2.</p>
               <p>But as to the later, there is a <hi>Satis ad testifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem,</hi> to teſtification, that is, To teſtifie the truth of our faith, the ſincerity of our obedience, and the uprightneſs of our hearts in the Service of God. When <hi>Abraham</hi> was ſo ready, upon Gods command, to offer up his Sonne <hi>Iſaac</hi> in ſacrifice to him, <hi>as to bring him to Mount</hi> Moriah, <hi>there to build an Altar, to lay the Wood in order upon it, and binde his Sonne to the Wood, to take the Knife in his hand, and to ſtretch forth his hand to Slay him:</hi> God ſtaies his hand, <hi>bids him hold his hand, proceed no further,</hi> Satis eſt, <hi>It is enough, for now I know that thou lovest me, ſeeing thou hast not refuſed to offer up thine onely Sonne in ſacrifice to me at my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</hi> Gen. 22. Here's a <hi>Satis ad testificationem,</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:59533:21"/>enough to teſtifie his love and obedience; and ſo, though none of Gods Saints and ſervants can reach to a <hi>Satis</hi> in reference to juſtification; yet as to the teſtification of the ſoundneſs of their faith, the ſincerity of their obedience, and the uprightneſs of their hearts in his Service, there is a <hi>Satis</hi> which they may reach to, and of which God himſelfe will teſtifie, and ſay, <hi>Satis est, It is enough.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond diſtinction in Anſwer to this Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, is this: There is another two-fold <hi>Satis:</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Firſt, <hi>Satis ad perfectionem.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Secondly, <hi>Satis ad acceptationem.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> Firſt <hi>enough, In reference to perfection.</hi> And,</p>
               <p>Secondly <hi>enough, In reference to acceptation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the former, <hi>Nunquam ſatis est,</hi> we can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver arrive enough as to perfection; Our Saviour hath ſet us a Coppy, that we can never come neer, <hi>Mat</hi> 6. <hi>Be you perfect as your heavenly Father is perfect.</hi> Alas! our higheſt perfection, is to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge our imperfection: and the beſt of us all, when we have done our beſt, to acknowledge, <hi>We are unprofitable ſervants:</hi> To confeſs, with the <hi>Centurion, Domine non ſum dignus, O Lord I am not worthy the leaſt of thy mercies:</hi> and with the <hi>Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can,</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:59533:21"/>to pray, <hi>Lord be mercifull to me a ſinner:</hi> ſo that if we look at perfection, <hi>Nunquam ſatis eſt,</hi> we ſhall never arrive to that degree, or height of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, as to ſay, <hi>Nunc ſatis eſt, It is now enough.</hi> But if we look at acceptation, bleſſed be God, there is a <hi>Satis,</hi> whereunto the Saints and ſervants of Almighty God may, and doe arrive, even in this life, through the mercy of God, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence of our Heavenly Father, which, where he ſees a willing mind, accepts of the will for the deed, and of what we can doe, inſtead of what we ſhould doe, which accepts according that a man hath, and not according to that he hath not: And ſo this rubb being removed, we paſs to the third Inference, which is this:</p>
               <p>That thus to have ſo done, the will of God will be our greateſt comfort in an evill day, when we ſhall ſtand in moſt need of it. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> found it ſo, when the Meſſage came to him by the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> from the Lord, <hi>That he ſhould ſet his houſe in order, for he must dye. O Lord remember, I have walked before thee with an upright and a perfect heart, and have done that which was good in thy ſight,</hi> Iſay 38.1, 3. <hi>Nehemiah</hi> found it ſo, who having done worthily for the people of God in obteining Commiſſion from the King of <hi>Perſia</hi> for
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59533:22"/>the redeeming of the <hi>Jews</hi> out of the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivity, and building the Walls of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> often comforts himſelfe with the remembrance of it, <hi>Nehemiah</hi> 13.14. <hi>Remember me, O my God in this, and blot not out the kindneſs that I have ſhewed to thy houſe.</hi> And <hi>verſe</hi> the 22. <hi>Remember me, O my God, concerning this alſo, and pardon me according to thy great mercy.</hi> And again <hi>verſe</hi> 31. <hi>Remember me, O my God, in goodneſs</hi> Indeed he needed not have put God in mind to remember him, the Lord would have remembred him, and his kindneſs ſhewed to his people, though he ſhould forget it: God is not unfaithfull that he ſhould forget the labour and love ſhewed unto his Saints. We ſee in <hi>Matthew</hi> 25 how he did remember it, when they had forgotten it that ſhewed it, <hi>ver.</hi> 42.43. <hi>When I was hungry, you gave me to eate: when I was thirſty, you gave me to drink: when I was naked, you cloathed me: ſick, and in priſon, you viſited me, and ministred unto me:</hi> this they had forgotten, and therefore asked, <hi>Lord, when ſaw we thee hungrty, or thirsty or naked, or ſick, and in priſon, and ministred unto thee?</hi> he remembred it, when they had forgotten it, and doth not onely remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber it, but reward it too, and now they finde the comfort of it. With ſuch a remembrance doth
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59533:22"/>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> comforts himſelfe, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7. <hi>I have fought the good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the faith. Henceforth is layd up for me a crowne of righteouſneſs:</hi> He was not afraid to ſing out his <hi>Cupio diſſolvi, I deſire to be diſſolved.</hi> Nor our Prophet in the Text, to make it his ſuite to the Lord, <hi>To take away his ſoule,</hi> when he <hi>remembred, how zealous he had been for the Lord God of Hosts,</hi> while he was in the body. The very <hi>Heathens</hi> were ſenſible of this, and it was a great incitement to them to juſtice and honeſty, and all morall vertue: <hi>Conſcientia benè acta vitae, multorumque benefactorum recordatio jucundiſſima eſt:</hi> The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of a life well ſpent, and the remembrance of much good done in his life time; O what a Cordiall it is to an old man, a dying man. And ſo is the contrary, the remembrance of a life ill ſpent, and of much evill done in a mans life time, as great a corraſive at ſuch a time: <hi>Thou writeſt bitter things against me, and makest me to poſſeſs the ſins of my youth, ſaith</hi> J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b, <hi>cap.</hi> 12.25. and he none of the worſt of men. Beloved, there will come a time when Conſcience awakened, and enlighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, will be ſerious with us, in calling us to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for things done in our life time, how we have ſpent our life, our time, and our Talents;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59533:23"/>what good we have done with them ever ſince we came into the world: And what a ſad account is this, when a man can give no better account to God, nor his own Conſcience, but thus, That he hath lived upon earth forty, or fifty, or ſixty, or ſeventy years, or more, to doe nothing, but eate, and drink, and ſleep, and play, or worſe, and ſpent his life, <hi>Aut nihil agendo,</hi> in doing nothing; <hi>Aut aliud agendo,</hi> in doing things impertinent, which is as good as nothing; <hi>Aut malè agendo,</hi> or in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evill, which is worſe then nothing, and now is going out of the world, before ever he hath thought of his errand, wherefore he came into it: If this be not to be an unprofitable ſervant, what is? and what his doome is, we have heard, and may reade, <hi>Matthew</hi> 25. Beloved, Let this Meditation teach us wiſedom, ſo to lay out our ſelves while we live in this world, ſo to improve our time, and our Talents, as that we may be able to give ſome account of them to God, and to our own Conſciences, ſo to live that we need not be afraid to dye, to be doing ſome good here in our life time, the remembrance whereof may yeeld us comfort in our ſickneſs, and hope in our death, ſo to lay out our ſelves in this world, that we may have ſomewhat to take to in the other
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59533:23"/>world, when we ſhall leave this, and all that we have in it, and ſo ſhall we be great gainers by the change.</p>
               <p>And ſo we have done with this third Inference alſo, deduc'd out of the Prophets third <hi>Satis eſt, It is enough,</hi> ſpoken in reference to what he had done, <hi>Satis feci, I have done enough.</hi> We now come to the fourth, as ſpoken in reference to his Age, and the years of his Life, <hi>Satis vixi, I have lived long enough.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In all likelihood, the Prophet was now an old man, and there are five things which perſwade us to think ſo.</p>
               <p>Firſt, He was Preſident of the Colledge of the Prophets, and the Prophets Children, ſuch as were bred up in an Academicall, or Studious way, whereby they might be fitted for that Office, when called unto it; he was Preſident over them, and that was not a Charge for a Novice or a Neo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phite to undertake.</p>
               <p>Secondly, He had wrought many great Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and done great and ſignall ſervices among the people of God, (as his ſtory teſtifieth,) which were not the work of a ſhort time, and he could not be leſs then thirty years old when he was firſt Anointed unto the Office of a Prophet, for that
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59533:24"/>was, <hi>Aetas Sacerdotalis,</hi> as St. <hi>Jerome</hi> calls it; and if it were ſo ſtill, the Church would receive no damage by it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, He was now commanded to Anoint <hi>Eliſha</hi> Prophet to ſucceed in his roome; an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that he had finiſhed his courſe in Propheſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and was now ready to reſigne.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, The laſt words of this Verſe ſeems to import as much, <hi>For I am no better then my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;</hi> they had their time here on earth, and are now dead and gone. I have had my time too, and what ſhould I doe now, but follow after them, and be gathered unto them, <hi>For I am no better then my Fathers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, Becauſe he makes it his requeſt, <hi>To be diſſolved,</hi> which if he were in his beſt Age, and ſtrength, and fit and able to ſerve God and his people in that high Office, he would not have done, nor could without ſin; in all theſe reſpects we may rationally conclude, he was now an old man. And although there be nothing in this world ſo deſireable as that it ſhould make a man in love with it in any ſtate of his life, and in his beſt years; yet much more when his beſt dayes are gone and paſt, when he is entring into that ſtate of life of which <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is but labour
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59533:24"/>and ſorrow,</hi> and thoſe years approach of which he ſhall ſay, <hi>I have no pleaſure in them,</hi> may he with good reaſon be content to leave the World, and make it his requeſt, <hi>That the Lord would take away his ſoule. When the keepers of the houſe trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the ſtrong men bow themſelves; when the grinders ceaſe, becauſe they are few, and they wax dark that look out at the windows: When the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Tree ſhall flouriſh, the Graſhopper ſhall be a burden, and all the daughters of ſinging ſhall be aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: When the Silver cord is lengthened, and the Golden Ewer broken, when the Pitcher is broken at the Well, and the Wheele broken at the Ciſterne, &amp;c.</hi> as that great Maſter of Wiſedom elegantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes old Age, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.3. &amp;c. then for an old <hi>Barzillai, to refuſe the pleaſures of the Court:</hi> Or an old <hi>Simeon,</hi> to ſing his <hi>Nunc dimittis.</hi> Or an aged <hi>Paul, To deſire to diſſolved:</hi> Or an old <hi>Elijah,</hi> to beſeech the Lord, <hi>To take away his ſoule,</hi> is no wonder, and all this as old Age meerly conſidered in it ſelfe, without any other grievances added to it to make it burdenſome, and irkſome, it is a burden to it felfe; but who ever ſaw it come, but attended with a world of infirmities to make it more tedious, Catarrs Rhumes, Aches, Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, akings in the Bones, Gouts, Dropſies, and in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59533:25"/>all theſe, inability to help it ſelfe; <hi>Senex bis puer,</hi> it is a ſecond Childhood, and 'tis a queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſecond be not worſe then the firſt. Upon theſe, and ſome other conſiderations, it hath often been my Prayer to the Lord God, and is at this inſtant, That he would not detain this ſoule of mine in this Tabernacle of Clay wherein it hath now lodged theſe ſeventy years and upward, unto extremity of old Age. But farther, If to all theſe there ſhould be added any externall grievances, poverty, and want, diſcontent in the Family, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience in prodigality of Children, diviſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Brethren, vexatious Suits, or the like, theſe were enough, not only to make an old man deſire diſſolution, but to haſten it, <hi>and to bring his gray baires with ſorrow to the Grave.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another diſcouragement to old Age that helps to take away the comfort of it is, That they are very apt to be deſpiſed, though it ſhould not be ſo, God hath ſtampt ſuch a reverend aſpect in the very face and gray haires of an old man, as ſhould command reverence from the younger ſort, if they were not unreaſonably uncivill; and hath commanded it too, <hi>Thou ſhalt riſe up before the boary head, and honour the perſon of an old Man; Age is honourable, a Crowne of glory,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi>)
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59533:25"/>the gray haires are the ſilver Crowne and Image of Gods eternity, who is deſcribed to have <hi>his head and his haire white as Wooll, or Snow,</hi> Revel. 1.14. where he is pleaſed ſo farr to honour old Age, as to take a ſimile from the <hi>gray haires,</hi> to ſhaddow forth his own Eternity: yet ſuch is the corruption and vitiouſneſs of men, to make that the matter of their reproach, which ſhould be of their honour: what more ordinary, then call ſuch, <hi>Old dotard, old foole, old any thing,</hi> that may ſound reproachfully: <hi>Honour thy Father that begat thee, and deſpiſe not thy Mother when ſhe is old,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi>) Prov. 23.22. implying, that ſhe is never more ſubject to be deſpiſed, then when ſhe is old.</p>
               <p>I will add but this one diſcouragement more which helps to take away from old men the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of their lives, and that is this, That they ſee the world grows weary of them, although they have deſerv'd never ſo well of it, yet, now they have done what good they can, and they ſee they can get no more good out of them, they grow weary of them, and would be ſhut of them. I have read of a barbarous Country, where, when men come to that extremity of old Age, that they grow uſeleſs, they knock them on the head,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59533:26"/>and bury them. We are not grown to that barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſme in <hi>England,</hi> but ſurely I doe beleeve, there are ſome that could wiſh it were ſo, ſome of their very neer relations, ſo their hand were not upon them, eſpecially if while they live they be any <hi>way</hi> troubleſome or chargeable to them; or at their death they look for ſome benefit by them: A ſtrange ingratitude, and moſt unreaſonable, that thoſe which receive moſt benefit from them, ſhould afford them leaſt reſpect, and be moſt wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them; but theſe are great diſcouragements to old Age, which may make them as weary of the World, as the World is of them, and wiſh with all their hearts, with our Prophet in the Text, <hi>That the Lord would take away their ſoule.</hi> I will conclude this Point, with my Advice to ſuch, though they need not be put in mind that their day is far ſpent, and the night cloſing upon them, their Sunne is ſet, and they but as a Candle ſpent to the end, and blinking within the ſocket, their gray haires and wrinkled cheeks, their dim eyes, trembling hands, and weak knees, reade unto them continuall Lectures of mortality, and adviſe them to withdraw out of the tumultuous Sea of this troubleſome World, and to put in to the Haven of quiet reſt, and repoſe; to give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59533:26"/>to Prayer and Meditation, to meditate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the vanity of the time paſt, the ſhortneſs of the time preſent, and Eternity to come; to ſet their Houſe and their Heart in order, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for a change at hand, and all the few dayes of their appointed time to waite till that change doe come, that ſo it may be unto them a happy change, and they may with hope and comfort re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne their ſoules into the hand of their Creator, and not be afraid to ſay with our Prophet in the Text, <hi>Lord take away my ſoule,</hi> which is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt it ſelfe, which in old <hi>Simeons</hi> Language, I call the Prophets <hi>Nunc dimittis:</hi> In which are theſe three things; Firſt, The Perſon, <hi>The Lord.</hi> Secondly, The Act, <hi>take away.</hi> Thirdly, The Object, <hi>my ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From the firſt note, He might not take it away himſelfe, his ſoule was not his own, he might not of his own head diſmiſs it himſelfe, though it were in him in never ſo much bitterneſs; but he muſt ſtay the time till God that gave it him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands it again, in the meane time, <hi>In his p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tience poſſeſs his ſoule, and all the dayes of his appointed time, waite untill his change ſhould come.</hi> It is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a deſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rate courſe of deſperate men, to ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date this Act of God by offering violence to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59533:27"/>themſelves, and ſo letting out their own ſoules, as <hi>Achitophel</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> did; ſuch think thereby to rid themſelves of ſome preſent griefe, or diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, by ridding-themſelves of their lives; but it is a deluſion of Satan to tell them ſo, herein they doe but leape out of the Frying Pan into the Fire, as the Proverbe is; for if this life did <hi>ſcourge them with ſcourges;</hi> that other, without the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary mercy of God, <hi>will torment them with Scorpions.</hi> It was ſaid of <hi>Hanniball, That he alwaies carried three or foure drops of ſtrong poyſon incloſed under the ſtone of his Ring, that at any time if he were hard ſet,</hi> (as <hi>Saul</hi> once was upon the loſs of the day in a Battell againſt the <hi>Philiſtines,) he might ſup them out, and prevent his falling into his enemies hands,</hi> as <hi>Saul</hi> then, upon the ſame occaſion, <hi>fell upon his Speare,</hi> and with the help of the fugitive <hi>Amalekite, Slew himſelfe.</hi> And that ſtout hearted Prince, which being taken Priſoner, and carried about by the Conqueror in a ſilver Cage, impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of his Captivity, and not having where with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to make away himſelfe, beat our his braines againſt the barrs of the Cage. We could inſtance in too many ſuch (God knows) which by hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, drowning, poyſoning, and other kinds of death, have made away themſelves; theſe our
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59533:27"/>Law calls, <hi>Felones de ſe,</hi> Felons of themſelves, and inflicts upon them as grievous a puniſhment as they are capable of being dead, by an ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious buriall: And yet I dare not ſay peremptori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of all ſuch, that they are certainly and eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly damned, though there be nothing viſible to us whereby we may judge otherwiſe of them; yet who can limit the mercies of the moſt high, or know what ſecret communication of ſpirit there may be in them, between the beginning of the act, and the end of it, <hi>Inter pontem &amp; fontem,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the bridge, &amp; the brook; between the ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup and the ground, mercy I ask't, mercy I found. <hi>Judas</hi> was not damned for hanging himſelfe, but for his I reaſon; but to leave them to their own Maſter and Maker to ſtand or fall.</p>
               <p>But Secondly, There are more <hi>Felones de ſe,</hi> ſelfe murderers, or which at leaſt are acceſſary to their own deaths then theſe, though the Law doe not call them ſo. As firſt, All lewd and ungodly perſons, which having not the feare of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes, take wicked courſes, commit rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries, burgleries, rapes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elones treaſons, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and other ſuch capitall Crimes, ſuch as that the Laws of the Land take hold of them, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut them off as not worthy to live upon the Earth,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59533:28"/>not among the Society of men: <hi>The cruell and blood thirſty man ſhall not live out halfe his dayes:</hi> all ſuch are at leaſt acceſſary to their own deaths.</p>
               <p>Secondly, All luxurious and intemperate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which by ſurfetting, drunkenneſs, and riotous living deſtroy themſelves, fill their bodies with noxious humours, which breed in them mortall diſeaſes, Sur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ets, Fevers, Dropſies, dead Palſies, and the like, by which they ſhorten their dayes. The <hi>Philoſopher</hi> obſerv'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> long agoe, That <hi>Plures gulâ quam gladio:</hi> There were more dyed by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance, then by the ſword.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, All quarrelſome Perſons, ſuch as are apt to give offence to others, and to provoke others to give offence to them, and ſo from words they fall to blows, or to challenge one another to fight Duells, in which, both parties are guilty of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by the ſixth Commandement; and as well he that is killed, as he that killeth, is at leaſt acceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to his own death: In none of theſe caſes can a man ſay confidently, <hi>That the Lord doth take away his ſoule,</hi> he throweth it away himſelfe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth himſelf.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From this the Prophets requeſt unto the Lord, <hi>To take away his ſoule;</hi> we may inferr, That though a man may not take away <hi>his own ſoul,</hi> yet
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59533:28"/>in ſome caſes, he may make it his Suit to Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, that he would doe it: So did old <hi>Simeon</hi> before mentioned: So did St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.6. So did <hi>Moſes Numb</hi> 11.15. So did <hi>Job, cap.</hi> 6.8.9. So did <hi>Jeremiah, cap.</hi> 20. So did <hi>Jonas, Jonah</hi> 3.3. So did our Prophet in the Text: I dare not juſtifie, nor excuſe all theſe which I have mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this their requeſt; I ſuppoſe that in ſome of them it proceeded from paſſion, and impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſo it was their infirmity, and blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy; yea, in this our Prophet himſelf, if there were not in this his requeſt a <hi>tacite</hi> ſubmiſſion to the will of God, it could not be excuſed, but it proceeded from infirmity in him; but this doth not infringe the truth of my inference,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That in ſome caſes the Saints and Servants of Almighty God, may without ſin make it their Suite to him,</hi> That he will take away their ſoules, <hi>that is, by death and diſſolution, ſeparate them from their bodies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, That ſo he may be taken out of a wicked world: Oh what a Hell is it to a pious foule to be ingag'd in a wicked world? For a <hi>Lot</hi> to live in <hi>Sodom:</hi> A <hi>David</hi> in <hi>Meſhech:</hi> It was a farr greater mercy which God ſhewed to <hi>Enoch,</hi> in taking him
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59533:29"/>out of the world from the Flood at hand, then that he ſhewed to <hi>Noah</hi> in preſerving him in it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, In caſe of long and laſting, ſharpe and griev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us Affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctions: Oh death, how ſweet is the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r membrance of thee to the ſoule that lives in bitterneſs? I doe not think the Lord did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it for ſin to <hi>Job,</hi> or <hi>Jeremy,</hi> that they were ſo weary of their bitter Lives, and did ſo often wiſh, <hi>That their change might come.</hi> Or, that King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth did ſin, when in his death bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſickneſs, he prayd ſo earneſtly, <hi>Lord take me out of this wretched World.</hi> Nor Dr. <hi>Hamond,</hi> who under the tortures of the Stone, whereof he dyed, was ſo often heard to ſay, <hi>Lord, make haſt:</hi> though I doubt not but in all theſe, there was implyed a <hi>tacit ſubmiſſion to the will of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, That a man may be taken away fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m the evill to come: This was a mercy promiſed to <hi>Joſiah</hi> upon his humiliation, (2 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.19.20.) as it was the miſery of his ſurviving Sonne <hi>Zede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> to ſee the evill which his Father was taken from, and to ſuffer in it. Wiſe men fore-ſee evill to come, in the cauſes of it, and in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of it: And the Lord mentions it as a mercy, <hi>That he will take them away from thoſe evills:</hi> and they may without ſin Pray for that mercy, <hi>Iſay</hi> 57.1.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:59533:29"/>
               <p> Fourthly, That they may be freed from the burden of the fleſh, and the bondage of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on inherint in it; that Ground Ivie in the Wall, which will never be pluckt out root and branch, till the Wall be thrown down: It was under the ſenſe of this that St. <hi>Paul</hi> cryes out, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24. <hi>O wretched man that I am: who ſhall deliver me from the body of this death?</hi> this will never be done, but by the death of this body.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, In extremity of old age, when a man becomes a burden to himſelfe, and others; when he is fallen into thoſe years of which <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>His life is nothing but labour and ſorrow,</hi> and the years of which he ſhall ſay, <hi>I have no pleaſure in them:</hi> when not onely his body grows weak, but his mind alſo, and his intellectuall faculties faile, his underſtanding weak, his apprehenſion dull, his memory unfaithfull, his affections Childiſh, and he becomes unſerviceable, not able to doe that good which he hath done, and ſhould doe; when a man becomes thus ſuperannuate, he may doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs without ſin, make it his ſuite to Almighty God, <hi>To take away his ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
               <p>This Meditation is uſefull to comfort, and to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59533:30"/>confirme us againſt the feare of death, either of our ſelves, or our friends; why ſhould we make that the object of our feare, which others have made the object of their hope and deſire? Holy men, wiſe men, good men, men that have had a great intereſt in the world, have been willing to lay down all, and to leave all, and made it their ſuite, that they might dye, in aſſurance of a change for a better life. To help us to paſs through this Gulfe with comfort and courage, weigh well but theſe two things:
<list>
                     <item>1. What a world we leave behind us, the <hi>Terminus à quo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. What a world we have before us, the <hi>Terminus ad quem:</hi> And theſe two conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations will make the paſſage through that <hi>medium</hi> eaſie.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, For the <hi>Terminus à quo,</hi> the world we leave behind us, a very ſink of ſin, a du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ghill of uncleanneſs: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, The whole World lyes in wickedneſs, as St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it <hi>but ſinne, and ſorrow, and travaile, and trouble, and malice, and miſchief,</hi> and that which may well make any wiſe man out of love with it,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59533:30"/>and even weary of it: The beſt things in it which men make moſt account of, have been weighed to our hands by the wiſeſt of the Sonnes of Men, and upon the tryall found, <hi>To be lighter then vanity it ſelfe;</hi> not onely vanity, <hi>but vexation of ſpirit.</hi> For firſt, They are all tranſitory. Secondly, They are not all ſatisfactory. Thirdly, All imbitter'd with ſo many croſs Ingredients, that there is no true contentment in them, nor true comfort to be taken out of them. We could ſhew you examples of the greateſt of men, Kings, Emperours, Lords of the world, ſuch as have had as much of the glory of it, and all other worldly good in it, as the world could give or lend; yet have ſeen ſo farr into the vanity and emptineſs of it, as to deſpiſe it, to lay down all, and take themſelves unto a private and monaſticall life, which is a death to the world, and the ſhaddow of death it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, For the <hi>Terminus ad quem,</hi> Conſider what a world (in dying) we are going to, it would require a world of time, and words to deſcribe it; the beſt deſcription of it is to deſcribe it to be ſuch (for the tranſcendency of the glory of it) as that it cannot be deſcribed, <hi>For neither hath the eye ſeen, nor the eare heard, nor can the heart of Man comprehend the great things that God hath prepared
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59533:31"/>for them that love him,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.9. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows it out in part, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22. where he ſhows the happineſs of the Church militant, in their communion with the Church triumphant, thus: <hi>But you are come to Mount Sion, and to the City of the living God, the Caeleſtiall Jeruſalem, and to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>numerable Angels: And to the Aſſembly and Congregation of the firſt borne, whoſe names are Written in Heaven, and to God the Judge of all, and to the ſpirits of juſt Men made perfect: And to Jeſus the Mediatour of the new Teſtament, and to the blood of ſprinkling, which ſpeaketh better things then the blood of</hi> Abel. Here's a deſcription in part of the Place, and Society which we ſhall goe to, when we ſhall come to be joyned with the Church tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant in glory; now be you well aſſured, that all things els there, are ſuitable to theſe, which muſt needs render it tranſcendently joyous, and glorious. O! if we could but draw the Curtaine of Heaven, and look in the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> to ſee the joy, and glory that is there, we would never care for this world more, the moſt pretious things in it would be deſpiſed in our eyes, our whole life would be nothing, but a <hi>Cupio diſſolvi, &amp; eſſe cum Chriſto: I deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt;</hi> and we would long for the time,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59533:31"/>when <hi>the Lord would take away our ſoul, that we might be tranſlated thither.</hi> I reade of one <hi>Cleombrotus,</hi> that hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Plato</hi> diſcourſing of the immortality of the ſoul, and the happines of the other life to come, <hi>Threw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf headlong off from a high Rock to quit himſelf of this life, that ſo he might enter into that other life, that</hi> Plato <hi>ſo much commended:</hi> And if a <hi>Heathen</hi> man could be ſo ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of advantaging himſelf by his change into the other life, upon thoſe weak grounds which <hi>Plato</hi>'s Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy could give, as to haſten his own death upon the hope of it: Surely we that are Chriſtians, and have better grounds to build our faith and hope upon, then any <hi>Plato</hi>'s Philoſophy could give; may with much more Comfort think on Death, with much more hope and confidence waite for it: and when it comes, bid it welcome, as our friend that comes to free our ſoul out of the priſon of the body, the ſole im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment of it's perfection, and to open the doore to let us into a better world, and into a better life. Thus of the Perſon to whom he makes his ſuit, <hi>The Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Now we are to conſider of the Act, <hi>Take away my ſoule.</hi> How doth the Lord take away ſouls?</p>
               <p>Not by annihilation, or reducing them to nothing, as at the firſt Creation: Nor by laying them a ſleep to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with their bodies, till the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the <hi>Arabians:</hi> Nor by a <hi>Metempſuchoſis,</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them into ſome other body, to informe them: Nor by fixing them, as Starrs in the Firmament: Nor
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:59533:32"/>by ſending them into purgatory, as the Papiſts teach: But thou that gaveſt it me, take it unto thy ſelf, either by thine own immediate power and grace, who art a Spirit, and the God of the ſpirits of all fleſh; or by the Miniſtery of thy good Angells, let them be ready to receive it, at the parting of it out of my body, as they did the ſoul of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and to carry it up to reſt and glory: Thus, <hi>Lord take away my ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From hence, note firſt, That our ſouls are immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, they dye not with the body; but when the body at the <hi>diſſolution returns to the earth, from whence it was taken the ſoul returns to God that gave it:</hi> All the expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of holy men dying, imports as much: <hi>Lord Jeſus receive my ſpirit,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Stephen. Father, into thy hands I commend my ſpirit,</hi> ſaith our Saviour: <hi>Lord take away ſoul,</hi> ſaith our Prophet; all expreſſing their faith in this truth, <hi>That their ſouls were immortal. Feare not them that can kill the body, and are not able to kill the ſoul,</hi> ſaith our Saviour: So then, the ſoul cannot be killed. Our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord diſputing with the <hi>Sadduces</hi> concerning the Reſurrection, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. tells them out of the Scriptures, <hi>That God was the God of</hi> Abraham, <hi>the God of</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and the God of</hi> Jacob, who were dead and buried a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years before; and from thence concludeth, <hi>the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality of the ſoul,</hi> inaſmuch, <hi>as God was not the God of who dead, but of the living,</hi> ver. 32. their ſpirits did never dye, their ſouls were ſtill alive, and in being, and he was their God.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:59533:32"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes.</hi> Firſt, It is of Uſe to quiet our ſpirits, and to ſatisfie our minds, ſometimes troubled upon the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the perplexities of Providence, in the croſs diſpenſation of evill and good, to the good and the evill here in this world; the unravelling of this Clue, of the ſouls immortality from the beginning to the end, will guide us through this Labyrinth, ſo that in the end, we ſhall ſay, <hi>The wayes of the Lord are right:</hi> when a day ſhall come, when it ſhall be ſaid to the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures</hi> of this world, which have had <hi>their portion</hi> in this life, as in <hi>Luke</hi> 16.25. <hi>Sonne, Rentember you have had your pleaſure in your life time, and my ſervants received pain: now they are comforted, and you are tormented.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. This Meditation is of Uſe to comfort, and to confirme us againſt the fear of death, either our own, or our friends, inaſmuch, as beleeving in the Lord, me <hi>ſhall live, though we dye: And he that liveth, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveth in him, ſhall never dye eternally:</hi> Indeed, we ſhall not dye at all, totally; for though we lay down our bodies into the earth to ſleep; yet our ſpirits ſhall not dye at all, but being delivered from the burden of the fleſh, ſhall live with the Lord, and be tranſlated into a ſtate of joy and feli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity, <hi>Et meliore ſui parte ſuperſtes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> erit,</hi> The better part is ſtill living, and therefore the Scripture will hardly call it a <hi>death,</hi> but <hi>a Sleep, a Change, a Diſſolution, a Departure, a Tranſlation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. It is of uſe for the contempt of this world, in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59533:33"/>which we have no ſurer footing, and of the beſt things of this world, of which we have no better hold, nor longer enjoyment, but for this ſhort &amp; uncertain life.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This Meditation of the immortality of the ſoul, is of ſpeciall uſe, to teach and to admoniſh to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare, and to provide for that our future condition, to lay up for our ſelves treaſure in Heaven, that we may have ſomething to take to, when we come into the other world, when we ſhall leave this, and all that we have in it behind us, to make us friends of the Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of iniquity, that when time comes, they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us into the everlaſting habitations, to lay here a good ſoundation againſt the time to come, that ſeeing our fouls are immortall, and ſhall have an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall being, it may be in well being; that ſeeing they ſhall live eternally, it may be in bliſs and happineſs, now is the time to provide for it: O how miſcrable will be the condition of thoſe ſouls, which having loſt their time here, when this life is ended, ſhall be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up into eternity, and all that while ſhall live in woe and miſery, in pain and torment, eaſeleſs, end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and remedileſs? How much better had it been for ſuch if they had never been born? Or being born, that their ſouls had dyed with their bodies? or living after them, there had been ſome period of time where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they might have been extinguiſhed? But when they muſt ſo continue for ever, <hi>That the worme ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59533:33"/>dye, nor the fire never goe out, that they ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in torment to all eternity:</hi> Who can conceive the miſery of it? That word <hi>eternity,</hi> into what a deep bottomeleſs gulfe doth it ſwallow up the mind that thinks upon it? Great wonder it is, and a miracle indeed, that a point of ſuch great importance, and high concernment, ſhould be no more heeded and regarded: Some live, as if they had no ſouls at all; or if they have any, that they are but as the ſouls of bruits, which periſh with their bodies; and well were it with them if they did ſo: they live, as if they never thought to dye, and dye, as if they never thought to riſe again; they have no hope in their death, nor any care of their immortall ſoules ever after. To theſe I ſay no more but this, <hi>Lord have mercy upon their poor miſerable ſoules, they will have time enough hereafter, when it is too late, to ſee their error, and to repent of this their ſtupidity and ſecurity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Note here the holy and heavenly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of the Saints and Servants of the Lord at their departure out of this life: <hi>O Lord, I have waited for thy ſalvation,</hi> ſaith the Patriarke <hi>Jacob</hi> upon his death bed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.18. <hi>Lord now let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thou thy ſervant depart in peace,</hi> (ſaid old <hi>Simeon, Luke</hi> 2.29.) <hi>for mine eyes have ſeen thy ſalvation.</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:59533:34"/>Saint <hi>Stephen</hi> the holy Martyr, with theſe words breath'd out his ſoule, <hi>Lord Jeſus receive my ſpirit, Acts</hi> 7.59. Our Lord himſelfe upon the Croſs, giving up the ghoſt, with theſe words breath'd his laſt, <hi>Father, into thy hands I commend my ſpirit, (Luke</hi> 23.46.) in ſenſe the ſame with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in the Text, <hi>Lord take away my ſoule.</hi> With ſuch holy expreſſions as theſe, did holy Men dying take their leave of the World, and breathe out their ſpirits. I could inſtance in many more, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Martyrs, Confeſſors, and other holy men and Women dying, ſome in my own hearing; others in the hearing of other Men, and recorded in the ſtories of their Lives and Deaths, with the gratious expreſſions utter'd by them in their death-beds, in words full of faith, full of hope, full of comfort, much to the edification of all that were preſent; and it is a great advantage to be preſent with ſuch men, at ſuch a time, for then are they moſt ſerious, then are their ſoules looſing from the priſon of their bodies, and are <hi>prominen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> (as it were looking out before they take their flight) then have they clearer Viſion of things then they had before, when they were in the cloſe priſon of their bodies, the light breaks in at the chinks, and at the doores and windows opening to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59533:34"/>let out the ſoule; then have many of the Saints had rare Diſcoveries, and Revelations, by which they have Propheſied of things to come; and the words of dying men, are much to be heeded and regarded. But if you would have the Lord to draw neer unto you in theſe wayes when you are dying, you muſt draw neer to God in his wayes while you are living; <hi>You muſt acquaint your ſelfe with God, and be at peace with him,</hi> as <hi>Eliphas</hi> ſpeaks in <hi>Job, cap.</hi> 22.21. <hi>you muſt live in commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with him, you muſt call upon his Name, prayſe him, and give him thanks, worſhip him, and doe his will, then will he own you; and be mercifull to you at that time, and draw neer unto you, and have a care of your ſoule that it ſhall not miſcarry: but he himſelfe will take it away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſecondly, If you would have the Lord to <hi>take away your ſoule,</hi> you muſt keep your ſoul with all diligence, and preſerve it pure, and undefiled, that the Lord may own it, and accept it, and place it among the holy ſouls of his Saints, and his redeemed ones. The Lord our God is a holy God, of pure eyes, which cannot behold any thing that is impure, but with indignation; and there is nothing more odious to him then ſinne and corruption, nor which renders us more abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59533:35"/>in his ſight: Compared therefore to Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie, to the Leopards ſpots, to menſtruous pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: If therefore our ſouls ſhall be preſented unto him ſtained with ſinne, polluted with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, defiled with ſpirituall leproſie of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, ſpotted with noyſome luſts and pleaſures; Will the Lord look at them? will he own them? will he accept them? Can we deſire the Lord, or hope that he will <hi>take away ſuch ſouls?</hi> or imploy his good Angels to fetch them, as he did to receive the ſoule of <hi>Lazarus</hi> and carry it into <hi>Abraham</hi>'s boſome? No, there are other ſoule-gatherers rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to take away ſuch ſouls, even thoſe which were imployed to fetch away the ſoule of the <hi>covetous rich Man</hi> in the Goſpel, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.20. If we would have the Lord to take away our ſouls, we muſt preſent them pure unto him, without ſpot, and blameleſs: They muſt be waſh't cleane in the blood of the Lambe, and cleanſed by the ſanctifying vertue of the holy Ghoſt; our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, the higheſt faculty of the ſoule, <hi>Muſt be purged from dead works, to ſerve the living God.</hi> We muſt purge our ſelves <hi>from all filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit, and grow up in true holineſs in the feare of the Lord:</hi> The <hi>Place</hi> which our ſouls are to <hi>goe to it holy, the Company holy, the exerciſes holy,</hi> and ſo
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59533:35"/>muſt our ſouls be alſo, that they may be ſuitable to all the reſt, and then the Lord will take away our ſouls, and place them amongſt them in joy, happineſs, and glory. Thus of <hi>The Act. The Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> followes, <hi>[My ſoule.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Branch.</hi> The ſoule is the ſpirituall part of Man, the principall and eſſentiall part whereof Man doth conſiſt, the fountaine of life, ſenſe, and motion, which by the ſpirits vitall, naturall, ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall, the ſouls curſitors running into all the parts of the body, actuates and informes it, and uſeth it as an Organ or Inſtrument whereby to performe it's ſeverall operations. This ſoule of man is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious in theſe ſeven reſpects.</p>
               <p>Firſt, In reſpect of the Fountaine of it, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds originally from the immediate breathing of God himſelfe: For when God had made Man of <hi>the duſt of the earth, he breath'd into him the breath of life, and Man became a living ſoul, Gen.</hi> 2.7.</p>
               <p>Secondly, In reſpect of the rare faculties of it, the Underſtanding, the Will, the Memory, the Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Reaſon, Judgement, Wiſedome, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Conſcience, the higheſt of all the reſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in both the parts of it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the one, <hi>The Treaſure;</hi> the other, <hi>The Soules Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouller, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:59533:36"/>
               <p> Thirdly, In reſpect of the immortality of it, it dyes not with the body; but being taken out of the body is preſerv'd unto Eternity.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, In reſpect of the Image of God once ſtampt upon it, which though miſerably defac't ſince by the fall, yet not ſo utterly raz'd out, but there are goodly lineaments of that Image yet left upon it: Neither is it ſo irrecoverable, but that by the ſpirit of grace, and the grace of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, it may be ſo repaired and renewed, as that the ſoule may be, and is ſaid ſtill, <hi>Thereby to be made partaker of the Divine Nature,</hi> 2 Peter 1.4. not in the ſubſtance of the Deity; but in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and righteouſneſs, wiſedome, knowledge, goodneſs, love, and light, which are as the beames of the Image of God ſhining upon it.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, In reſpect of the purchaſe of it, <hi>It is the price of blood,</hi> not of Bulls, and Goats, <hi>but of the Divine blood of Jeſus Chriſt our Redeemer,</hi> 1 Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 1.19.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, The pretiouſneſs of ſouls may appear, by the pains and coſt that Satan and his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments will be at to gaine a ſoule; they will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs Sea and Land to gaine a ſoule; give a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for a ſoule. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.8. <hi>All the Kingdoms of the world, with the glory of them,</hi> Omnia haec tibi
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59533:36"/>dabo, <hi>All theſe things will I give thee, if thou wilt fall down and worſhip me,</hi> ver. 9.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, By the great care that Almighty God hath taken to preſerve ſouls, and to ſave them from periſhing; he hath given his Word to direct them, his Miniſters to inſtruct them, his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments to confirme them, his Spirit to guide them, and his Angels to guard them, and all this to preſerve them, and to ſave them from periſhing.</p>
               <p>In all theſe reſpects, it appears that ſouls are pretious: Our bleſſed Lord, which well knew the price of ſouls, lays one ſoule in one ballance, and the whole world in the other againſt it; and upon the tryall, tells us, That one ſoule weighs downe the whole world in the other ſcale: <hi>What ſhall it profit a Man to win the whole world, and to loſe his foule?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
               <p n="1">1. It ſhould teach all men to value their ſouls according to the worth of them, and not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them, nor to paſs them away ſo careleſly, and inconſiderately, as ordinarily men doe to their eternall undoing: Some deſperately wound them to death, by deſperate, willfull, and preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſins: <hi>Heale my ſoule, for I have ſinned againſt
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59533:37"/>thee:</hi> implying, that by ſinne he had wounded it: Some ſell their ſouls, and that for triflles, that are worth nothing; for pleaſures of ſinne, which are but for a ſeaſon; for treaſures of wickedneſs, which profit nothing; for ſatisfying ſome ſinfull luſts, which are worſe then nothing: Some give away their ſouls for nought, for ſins in which there is neither pleaſure, nor profit; as Curſing, Swearing, idle and lewd Communication, and the like, theſe make the worſt bargains of all: Others pawne their ſouls, they will give themſelves liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to walk in the ſight of their own eyes, and in the wayes of their own heart, and to ſerve their luſts but for ſuch a time, and then they will take up, and repent, and recover themſelves, and their ſouls again, as if it were in their own will, and power, to come in when they will: All theſe make ill bargains, and paſs away their pretious ſouls for a thing of nought, which all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the world cannot buy again: We ſee this, we heare it, and we condemne them for it; yet are there dayly amongſt us that are guilty of the ſame folly, and by Covetouſneſs, Voluptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Ambition, Malice, Perjury, and the like, ſell themſelves, and their ſouls for leſs, and paſs them away upon worſe termes then they have done:
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59533:37"/>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> ſold himſelfe for <hi>an Apple: Eſau</hi> for a <hi>Meſs of Pottage: Achan</hi> for a <hi>Wedge of Gold: Ahab</hi> for a <hi>Vineyard: Judas</hi> for <hi>thirty pieces of ſilver.</hi> How many are there to be found amongſt us which for leſs matters will lye, will ſweare, will forſweare, will ſteale, deceive, cheate, and coſen, and what not? That to ſatisfie their baſe, ſinfull, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable luſts, and humours, will part with a good Conſcience, forfeit the favour of God, their hope of Heaven, their intereſt in Chriſt, and in the Goſpel, ſell themſelves, and ſoules, and all for leſs then a Meſs of Pottage. The reſolution of <hi>Balaam</hi> was good and honeſt, juſt and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, if he had kept it as well, <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.13. <hi>If</hi> Balak <hi>would give me his houſe full of ſilver and gold, I would not goe beyond the Word of the Lord, to doe more or leſs:</hi> Let it be the reſolution of every ſoul, and God give us grace and power to keep it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Are ſouls ſo pretious? Then let us look to them carefully, preſerve them charily, as we would doe our chiefeſt Jewells; Keep thy ſoule with all diligence, examine the ſtate of it, ſee it want no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of that which ſhould be for the happineſs, and the proſperity of it: Our care is much for the body, <hi>What ſhall we eate, what ſhall we drinke, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall ſhall we be clothed?</hi> in the meane while the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:59533:38"/>ſoule is neglected, ſet by, and leaſt look't after; but as our Saviour ſaies in a like caſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.25. <hi>Is not the body better then the rayment?</hi> So ſay I, <hi>Is not the ſoule better then the body? Is there any compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon between the Jewell and the Cabinet that it is layd up in?</hi> It was <hi>Martha</hi>'s reproofe, <hi>That ſhe cared for many things more then ſhe needed: And for the one thing that was more neceſſary, leſs.</hi> It is our juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe in this caſe; We enquire after the health and welfare of our friends, and after their proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, how they thrive in this world; but without any regard to their ſpirituall eſtate, and the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and proſperity of their ſouls. St. <hi>John,</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Gaius,</hi> with a more ſpirituall ſalutation, hath a more ſpeciall eye to the proſperity of his ſoule; <hi>Beloved, I wiſh chiefly that thou doe proſper, as thy ſoule proſpereth,</hi> 3 <hi>John</hi> 1.2. <hi>David</hi> did more rejoyce in the good the Lord had done for his ſoule, then for all the good he had done to him, and for him in his body, in his eſtate, or in any other his relations: <hi>Hearken to me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>all you that feare God, and I will tell you what the Lord hath done for my ſoule:</hi> The Lord had done great things for him otherwiſe, and he could have given them a large narrative of them; but in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of his great favours to him, he paſſes
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59533:38"/>by all theſe, and mentions the other, as farr greater then all the reſt, <hi>I wil tell you what the Lord hath done for my ſoul:</hi> So the care of all thoſe holy men dying, which I have mentioned, was chiefly for the ſafety of their ſouls, <hi>Lord Jeſus receive my ſpirit, Acts</hi> 7.59. <hi>Father into thy hands I commend my ſpirit.</hi> And in the <hi>Text, Lord take away my ſoul:</hi> Though the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the Saints dying, are not to be neglected, but decently to be inter'd, as in hope and expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a bleſſed <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> as the body of St. <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> was, and the body of our bleſſed Lord; yet the care they had of their ſouls, ſwallowed up all the care of their bodies, ſo that it is not ſo much as mentioned by them, nor by our Prophet in the <hi>Text,</hi> but onely his ſoul, <hi>Lord take away my ſoul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Are ſouls ſo pretious? Then this is a ſevere ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition to us (that have undertaken, <hi>Curam ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum,</hi> the care of ſouls) to look well to our <hi>charge,</hi> as ſuch as muſt give an account of the greateſt truſt in the world, even <hi>the ſouls of Gods people com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to our charge.</hi> I cannot but tremble, when I reade St. <hi>Paul</hi> giving up his account to God, to his Peoplae, and to his own Conſcience in this matter, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.26. <hi>I am free from the blood of all Men.</hi> What blood doth St. <hi>Paul</hi> here ſpeak of? he was no <hi>Sword Man,</hi> there was no fear of his ſhedding any mans
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59533:39"/>blood by violence: How comes he to clear himſelf from blood? (Bel.) the blood here meant is more pretious then the life-blood of man can be, it is the <hi>blood of ſouls:</hi> implying, <hi>That if he had not faithfully, and conſcionably performed the duties of his Paſtorall charge amongſt them, he had been guilty of the blood of ſouls.</hi> Oh let this ſink deep into our hearts, that we may not become guilty of the blood of ſouls: How earneſtly ought we to endeavour the ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our people, as of our ſelves? and at the hour of death to Pray, <hi>That the Lord would be mercifull to them, and take away their ſouls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But here now ariſeth a great queſtion, a grand inquiry, not without great caution and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety to be reſolved, <hi>Touching the ſtate of ſouls ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated, and taken out of the body, What becomes of them afterward? Whether upon their ſeparation they doe preſently enter into that ſtate in which they are to remain, and continue during this vaſt ſpace of Eternity, without all change or alteration of their condition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer no; For the ſoule of man from the time of it's firſt being in him, whether by Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, or by infuſion, or by traduction generation I diſpute not; nor of the praeexiſtence of it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, an Opinion that hath great Patrons too, eſpecially among the Philoſophers, the Gymnoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſts
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59533:39"/>of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the Brachmans of <hi>India,</hi> the Magi of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and the <hi>Jewiſh Cabaliſts,</hi> and among them, ſome Chriſtians alſo, <hi>Origen</hi> for one; but I wave that diſpute too: But I date my diſcourſe from the ſouls firſt being in the body, from that beginning it paſſes it's immortality under three conditions, or a three-fold eſtate, every one of them different from other. The firſt is the ſtate of the foule during the time of it's being in the body, which it doth actuate and informe. The ſecond is the ſtate of it between the time of the ſeparation of it from the body, by diſſolution, and there union of it again with the body at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, &amp; the day of Judgement. And the third is from that day to Eternity, and for ever after: That theſe three ſtates of the ſoule are different one from the other is evident enough: Of the firſt of theſe we have experience in this life, while our ſouls are in our bodies, which are given unto us to actuate, and informe them, and to uſe them as Organs, or Inſtruments for glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying God by them, and doing good: <hi>Glorifie God in your bodies, and in your ſpirits, for they are his,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.20. this is done, by giving up the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the one, and the parts of the other: <hi>Not as members of unrighteouſneſs to unrighteouſneſs, but
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:59533:40"/>as inſtruments of righteouſneſs unto holineſs,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly as we have ſo done, ſhall we give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count unto God, in the day of account: <hi>For we muſt all appear before the judgement ſeat of Chriſt, to render an account for the things done in the body, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be good or evill,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.15. Therefore now is the time of working, now is the time of doing our ſelves good, now is the time of laying a good foundation for the time to come, now is the time of laying up that, which may be for the furtherance of our account then; now in this firſt eſtate of the ſoule, while it is in the body, muſt we provide for the well-being of it in the ſecond eſtate, and in the third, and to Eternity: Now as this firſt eſtate of the ſoule in the body is different from the ſecond eſtate of it, as it is ſeparated from the body; ſo is that ſecond eſtate of it out of the body different from the third eſtate of it, when it ſhall be re-united to the body again, and put into that eſtate in which it ſhall remain for ever, and to all Eternity. It is the generall Opinion of men, but withall, a generall miſtake, That as ſoon as ever the ſoule is ſeparated from the body, it paſſes immediately into that eſtate either of joy &amp; glory, or of miſery and torment, in which it ſhall remain for ever, without any alteration. True it
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:59533:40"/>is, That at the ſeparation of the ſoule from the body, there is a particular judgement paſſes upon it, by which it is made known to it, what ſhall become of it Eternally, and is preſently put into the beginnings, either of the one, or the other, and into a ſtate previous to that third eſtate, in which it is to remain for ever, without alteration: but that either the ſouls of wicked men are imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately upon their ſeparation from the body caſt into that extremity of miſery and torment which is prepared for them: Or that the ſouls of the juſt doe then paſs into that heigth of joy and glory which God hath prepared for them, I doe confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently deny, and ſhall prove the contrary in both the parts of it. And firſt for the ſouls of wicked men, that they are not upon their ſeparation from the body caſt into that extremity of torment which is prepared for them: I prove by an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>à Majori,</hi> thus:
<q>
                     <hi>The very Devills themſelves are not yet caſt into that extremity of torment that they are condemned unto. Therefore the ſouls of wicked men are not immediately upon their ſeparation caſt into thoſe torments.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The Conſequence of this Argument is clear, for no man will judge the ſtate of wicked men to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:59533:41"/>be worſe then the ſtate of Devills. The Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent I prove by two clear teſtimonies of Scripture; The firſt out of St. <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.29. where thoſe fierce Devills which had poſſeſſed two men among the <hi>Gergeſens,</hi> ſeeing Chriſt comming towards them, are ſtricken with terror at his preſence, and cry out, <hi>What have we to doe with thee, Jeſus thou Sonne of God? Art thou come to torment us before the time?</hi> They knew they were condemn'd to torment, but there was a time ſet when they ſhould be caſt into it, but that time was not yet come; and therefore ſeeing him comming towards them, they cry out againſt him, as if he came to antedate their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, by caſting them into it before the time, <hi>Art thou come to torment us before the time?</hi> The other proofe is both a confirmation of the truth in hand, and an illuſtration of this Text: It is in the Epiſtle of <hi>Jude,</hi> ver. 6. <hi>The Angels alſo which kept not their firſt eſtate, but left their own habitation, he hath reſerved in chains of darkneſs, unto the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great day;</hi> where you have the time when they ſhall be caſt into that extremity of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto which they are condemned, at the <hi>judgement of the great day;</hi> and the eſtate that they are in, in the mean time, they are reſerv'd in chains of darkneſs, the <hi>chains</hi> noting, the ſafe keeping
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59533:41"/>and ſecuring of them, that thus can no ways make their eſcape: And the <hi>darkneſs,</hi> noting their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall and uncomfortable condition all that while: <hi>They are reſerv'd in chains of darkneſs, unto the Judgement of the great day;</hi> an expreſſion borrowed from the ſtate of condemned priſoners, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they are condemn'd, are ſecured in chains or fetters, and caſt into the dungeon, and there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved unto the day of Execution. And this is a ſufficient proofe of the truth of this aſſertion in the firſt part of it, as touching the ſouls of wicked men, <hi>That the ſtate of their ſouls, from the day of their ſeparation from their bodies, untill the day of Judgement, is not the ſame that it ſhall be after that day, though it be a woefull eſtate too, as will farther appear in the ſequel of this diſcourſe.</hi> We are now to make good this Propoſition in the other part of it, Concerning the ſouls of the juſt, that they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not preſently upon their diſſolution into the fullneſs of joy and glory intended them, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them. And for that I alledge, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.9.10.11. where at the opening of the fifth Seale, St. <hi>John</hi> ſees under <hi>the Altar, the ſouls of them that were killed for the Word of God, and for the teſtimony which they maintained. And they cryed with a loud voyce, ſaying, How long Lord, how long, holy and true,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:59533:42"/>doſt thou not Judge, and avenge our blood on them that dwell on the Earth? And long white robes were given to every one, and it was ſaid unto them, that they ſhould reſt for a little ſeaſon, untill their fellow ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and their brethren that ſhould be killed, (even as they were) were fulfilled.</hi> This Scripture makes for our purpoſe all along; For firſt, Who are they that here complain? the Text ſayes, <hi>They were Martyrs,</hi> and thoſe are Saints of the firſt lift; and if their ſouls were not received into the fulneſs of joy and happineſs at their diſſolution, what ſouls are? But that they were not, it appears, Firſt, By their complaint, <hi>How Long Lord? how long?</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, By the anſwer given unto them, perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſtill <hi>to waite for a ſeaſon, and to poſſeſs their ſouls with patience, til the reſt of the number of their brethren were accompliſhed,</hi> without whom they could not be made perfect, and that could not be till the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and the Generall Judgement at the great day. <hi>Aquinas</hi> doth excellently deſcribe <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum bonum</hi> or the higheſt felicity to be, <hi>Quies Mentis;</hi> or <hi>Acquieſcentia Mentis in ultimo fine;</hi> the reſt, or acquieſcence of the mind in the laſt end, beyond which nothing can be deſired to make it more happy: But thoſe ſouls which yet cry, <hi>How long Lord? how long?</hi> doe declare, That they have
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:59533:42"/>not yet attained their <hi>ultimate</hi> end; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they doe not perfectly <hi>acquieſce,</hi> but are in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of a farther degree of fuller happineſs yet to be given unto them. And thus I have made good this <hi>Propoſition,</hi> in both the Parts, <hi>That the ſouls ſeparated from the body by Death, are not in the ſame ſtate from the time of their ſeparation, to the time of their re-union again at the day of Judgement, that they ſhall be in, after that day, to all eternity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But then, me thinks I heare you ask me, <hi>In what ſtate are they then during that time? Where are they? Or what becomes of them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to this <hi>Quaerie,</hi> I ſhall endeavour to ſatisfie you too, and that, <hi>Ad partes,</hi> to both the parts of it, both as it concerns the ſouls of the juſt, and the ſouls of the unjuſt and wicked men. And firſt, as to the ſouls of wicked men; If you ask me <hi>where?</hi> or <hi>in what ſtate they are?</hi> I anſwer, They are in the ſame ſtate, and in the ſame places that the evill Angells are in, and what that was, you heard even now out of <hi>Jude</hi> 6. they are ſecured in priſon, they are with them <hi>reſerved in chains unto the judgement of the great day.</hi> For proofe of this, take theſe two Scriptures; the firſt in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.19. The ſecond in <hi>Luke</hi> 12.20. In the firſt, St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking of the death of Chriſt, ſaith thus, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. <hi>Christ
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:59533:43"/>alſo ſuffered for ſinners, the juſt for the unjuſt, that he might bring us to God, who was put to death as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the fleſh, but was quickned in the Spirit. By which ſpirit alſo, he went and Preach't to the ſpirits in priſon,</hi> v. 19. If ye ask, <hi>What ſpirits?</hi> he tells you, ver. 20. <hi>Thoſe ſpirits which in time past were diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient:</hi> In what time? In the times of <hi>Noah,</hi> and before the Flood, for ſo it followeth; <hi>When once the long ſuffering of God abode in the dayes of</hi> Noah, <hi>while the Ark was preparing: wherein few, that is, eight perſons were ſaved from periſhing in the waters.</hi> There you have St. <hi>Peter</hi> plainly interpreting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that the ſpirits here mentioned, are the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the ſinners of the old world, which peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the Flood, but their ſpirits periſhed not, neither were they preſently ſent to the Lake of everlaſting Burnings, but they are ſecured in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as the evill Angels are, and ſo reſerved unto the Judgement of the great day. That place in St <hi>Luke,</hi> ſpeaks the ſame thing, where the Voyce is heard ſpeaking to the ſecure Epicure, ſinging a <hi>requiem</hi> to his own ſoule, <hi>Soule, take thine eaſe, eate, drink, and be merry, thou hast goods layd up for many years:</hi> Alas! he dreams of many years, when he hath not many hours to live: <hi>Stulte hac nocte, Thou foole, this night ſhall they fetch away thy ſoule: then
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:59533:43"/>whoſe ſhall theſe things be?</hi> Nay, Whoſe ſhalt thou be? <hi>This night ſhall</hi> they <hi>fetch away thy ſoule:</hi> Which <hi>they?</hi> The evill Angels. When good men dye, the good Angells are ready to receive their ſouls, as they did the <hi>ſoule of Lazarus,</hi> Luke 16. <hi>and carry them into</hi> Abraham's <hi>boſome.</hi> But when wicked men dye, the evill Angells fetch away their ſouls, <hi>Thou foole, this night ſhall they fetch away thy ſoule:</hi> And whither (think you) were they to carry it? but to their own Quarters, to thoſe Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in which themſelves are ſecur'd, as <hi>in chains unto the judgement of the great day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But then here ariſeth another Queſtion, <hi>What thoſe Priſons are?</hi> Or, <hi>Where it is, that they are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured unto that day?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to this I Anſwer. There are three vaſt, large, and ſpacious Priſons, in which the evill An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells are ſecured, and with them the ſouls of wicked men, unto the Judgement of the great day. And they are,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>The Aire.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>The Earth.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>The Sea.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, The <hi>Aire,</hi> with all the ſeverall Regions of it, into which the Apoſtate Angells were bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed:
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59533:44"/>When for their rebellion againſt their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, they were expell'd out of Heaven. For this, ſee St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians, cap.</hi> 6.12. <hi>You wreſtle not against fleſh and blood, but against Principalities and Powers, and ſpirituall wickedneſſes in high places:</hi> And what? or who are thoſe ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall wickedneſſes, but thoſe evill ſpirits? And what are thoſe high places, but the Regions of the Aire? And therfore is the Principall of the Devills, called, <hi>The Prince that ruleth in the Aire;</hi> for even amongſt them there is Order, and ſubordination: We reade of a <hi>Prince among Devills,</hi> Epheſ. 2.2.</p>
               <p>The ſecond of thoſe Priſons, is, The <hi>Earth;</hi> and therein firſt, The vaſt and howling Wilderneſſes, and Places uninhabited, where no foot doth tread, but where Oſtriches doe dwell, where <hi>Ziim</hi> doth boade, and the <hi>Satyres</hi> dance.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The vaſt caverns and concavities within the earth, amongſt which the hollow mountains of <hi>Aetna, Veſuuius,</hi> and in <hi>Ireland</hi> that hollow vault, called, Saint <hi>Patriarchs Purgatory,</hi> famous in ſtory: But in <hi>America</hi> many ſuch, and more evident dens of Daemons: But above all theſe, the vaſt hollowneſs in the very heart, and Center of the Earth; for who knows what vaſt and ſpatious receptacles there may be for ſuch ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits?
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59533:44"/>It is not unreaſonable, nor againſt any Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Faith, or of Scripture to conceive, That there is in the very heart and Center of the Earth, ſuch a vaſt hollowneſs, both for a fit receptacle for ſuch ſpirits, and by which that vaſt and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty body is buoy'd up that it ſink not any way to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Circumference on any ſide, though no way ſupported, neither by Poaſts, nor Pillars. What is it that ſuſtains the vaſt and weighty Ships in the Sea, with all the Anchors, Ordnance, and Fraught in them, but the hollowneſs of them? What is it that ſuſtains the Clouds in the Aire, infinitely greater, and more weighty then they, ſo as they fly to and fro, but as <hi>bottles in the Aire,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks, or <hi>like bladders full of winde,</hi> that they fall not down in great daſhes, enough to make ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Deluge, but the hollowneſs of them? That ſuch a hollowneſs there is in them, appears by the Lightning, the Thunder, and the Thunder-bolts, and the ſpirituall vapour that proceeds out of them, when they break of ſuch force, that it pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrates, and burns, and breaks, and tears in peeces all that it lights upon: And who can deny, but it is agreeable to reaſon, that there may be ſuch a hollowneſs in the heart of the earth, whereby it may, by the power and providence of the Creator,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:59533:45"/>be ſuſteined in the place which he hath appointed for it; and alſo be a fit receptacle of evill ſpirits, where they may be ſecured as in a Priſon, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved unto the Judgement of the great day. In the Apoſtolicall Creed, we profeſs to beleeve, <hi>That Chriſt deſcended into Hell.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>He deſcended</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>into the lower parts of the Earth:</hi> This cannot be underſtood of the deſcent of his body by his buriall, that ſcarce went into the Earth at all, but was layd in the Sepulchre which <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> had made for himſelfe in his Garden, which was above the ground, or, at leaſt, the moſt part of it, if any part at all of it were under, or within the ground, it was not ſo low, as that we may ſay of it, <hi>It was in the lower parts of the Earth.</hi> How then will you underſtand this Article of our <hi>Lords deſcent into Hell,</hi> except you underſtand it of his Soule, and of his Spirit? And where will you finde this Hell more agreeable to Scripture, and Reaſon, then as I have deſcribed it? and that <hi>by his Spirit, he went to Preach to the ſpirits in priſon there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third vaſt Priſon wherein the <hi>evill Angells are ſecured unto the day of the generall Judgement,</hi> is, <hi>The Sea;</hi> for there are <hi>Sea Spirits,</hi> as well as <hi>Land Spirits,</hi> or <hi>Aeriall Spirits.</hi> When the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
<pb facs="tcp:59533:45"/>being in a Ship, ſaw Chriſt coming towards them walking upon the Sea, the Text ſayes, <hi>They were troubled, and thought they had ſeen a Spirit, Mat.</hi> 14.26. whereby it appears, That there were <hi>Spirts</hi> that did appear in the <hi>Sea,</hi> as well as on the <hi>Land.</hi> And in St. <hi>Mathew</hi> 8. we reade, <hi>That the Devills being caſt out of the man which they had poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed, entred into an Heard of Swine, and carried them headlong into the Sea:</hi> by which it ſeems, there was their abode. And in <hi>Mark</hi> 5. which by many circumſtances ſeem not to be the ſame ſtory, with this of St. <hi>Matthew:</hi> we reade, <hi>Of a whole legion of Devills, entring into a Heard of no leſs then two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Swine, and carrying them with great violence into the Sea:</hi> theſe were <hi>Sea Spirits,</hi> whoſe abode was in the <hi>Sea,</hi> which is the third Priſon wherein theſe <hi>evill Angells</hi> are ſecur'd, and confin'd unto the Judgement of the great day, and with them, the ſouls of wicked men, both to be brought in, and judged at that general Aſſizes, which though they be not till then caſt into the Lake of everlaſting burnings; yet is their condition in the mean time woefull, and miſerable: 'Tis miſerable to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how wilfully they have forſaken their own mercy, and what opportunity they have loſt of preventing this their miſery, never to be recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:59533:46"/>nor recalled: 'Tis miſerable to lye in Priſon, in ſuch a Priſon, and for ſuch Crimes of which they know themſelves they ſhall be found guilty at that day, and condemn'd to ſuffer the venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of everlaſting ſire: 'Tis miſerable to ſee Hell open before them, and ready to receive them: 'Tis miſerable in the mean time to lye under the wrath of the Almighty, and under the torments of a wounded ſoule: Yet neither are the torments of the ſouls of wicked men, during this time of their ſeparation from their bodies all aequall; as neither ſhall they be after the generall Judgement, as ſhall be ſhewed in the ſequel of this Treatiſe; but in the mean while, (having ſhewed you the ſtate of the ſouls of wicked men) It now reſts that I ſhould ſhew you, What is the ſtate of the ſouls of juſt men, from the time of their ſeparation from their bodies, till the time of their re-union again with their bodies at the day of the Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>And in anſwering to this inquiry, the Scripture gives us ſome light in foure expreſſions; <hi>When the body returns to duſt from whence 'twas taken, the ſpirit returns to God that gave it,</hi> ſaith <hi>Soloman, Eccleſ.</hi> 12.7. <hi>The Angells receive it, and carry it into</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham's <hi>boſome,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Luke, cap.</hi> 16.22. <hi>It is layd under the Altar,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>John, Rev.</hi> 6.9. <hi>It is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:59533:46"/>into Paradiſe,</hi> ſaith our Saviour to the penitent theeſe upon the Croſſe, <hi>Luke</hi> 23.43. All theſe are moſt comfortable, and heavenly expreſſions, ſetting forth the bleſſed and happy eſtate of the ſouls of the juſt which they enter into, when they are delivered from the burden of the fleſh, the great impediment of their perfection; yet they doe not all amount to this, That upon their ſeparation they paſs into the higheſt Heaven, and into the fruition of the immediate viſion of God, and that fulneſs of joy and glory, that they ſhall enter into at the laſt day, when it ſhall be ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, enter into the inheritance of the Kingdom prepared for you from the beginning of the world.</hi> For we cannot imagine that theſe words are ſpoken onely in reference to the bodies, then newly rayſed out of their graves; but to the whole man, body and ſoule united to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and ſo to the entire perſons of them, <hi>Come ye bleſſed, enter into the Kingdom.</hi> For that of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, That the ſoule returns to God that gave it,</hi> it is true; that is, It is taken up into the higher Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and is in neerer communion with God then it was before, it is admitted neerer into his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, it is taken into his more immediate care to diſpoſe of it, in a place and ſtate of bliſs and feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:59533:47"/>of joy and glory, even preſently upon the ſeparation of it from the body: For that of Saint <hi>Luke, That the Angells received the ſoule of</hi> Lazarus: the meaning is, That he was gathered unto the reſt of the faithfull, of which <hi>Abraham</hi> is ſaid to be the Father, and carried to a place of reſt, intimated by <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>boſome: Sinus Patriarcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum receſſus, quidam eſt quietis aeternae,</hi> Ambr. For that of St. <hi>John Rev.</hi> 6. <hi>Where he ſees the ſouls of the Martyrs under the Altar:</hi> the meaning is, That they were in a place of ſecurity, where no evill ſhould touch them, as in the third of the book of <hi>Wiſedom, The ſouls of the righteous are in the hand of God, and no evill ſhall touch them, v.</hi> 1. The <hi>Altar</hi> was an <hi>Aſylum, a place of refuge and protection,</hi> 1 Kings 2.28. The ſouls of theſe Martyrs were <hi>ſeen under the Altar,</hi> to intimate their ſecurity, their ſafety, no evill might touch them.</p>
               <p>As to that ſaying of our Lord, to the penitent theefe upon the Croſs, <hi>This day ſhalt thou be with me in Paradiſe:</hi> I give theſe two anſwers. Firſt, That Paradiſe is not ſo limited to the higheſt Heaven, where the Throne of God is, but that it may comprehend ſome other place adjacent to it, where he might be in joy and felicity with Chriſt, who as to his Divine Nature is every where; the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:59533:47"/>word ſignifieth, <hi>A place of pleaſure:</hi> and ſuch are the places aſſigned to be the receptacles of the ſouls of the juſt, when they are ſeparated from their bodies. I anſwer ſecondly, That for the ſouls of <hi>Enoch</hi> before the Law, and of <hi>Elijah</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, and of this penitent theefe under the Goſpel: I doe not deny, but they might have ſpeciall priviledge in the tranſlation of them, that the Lord in their examples might give good aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to all beleevers, and to all the juſt that ever have, or ſhall live in any Age of the World, whether before the Law, under the Law, or ſince the Law, as well of their aſcenſion, and glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as of their reſurrection: As to this penitent theefe in particular, dying with him upon the Croſſe, that he might ſhew a <hi>ſpecimen</hi> of the power of his death, in ſaving, juſtifying, and glorifying penitent ſinners, though never ſo great offenders; but then we muſt remember with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that theſe were peculiar priviledges of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular perſons: And, <hi>Privilegia ſunt paucorum,</hi> the Civill Law will tell us, <hi>That Priviledges are the portion but of few:</hi> This doth not weaken the truth of my aſcertion, That the ſouls of juſt men dying, doe not immediately upon the ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of them from the body, paſs into the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:59533:48"/>Heaven, nor to the higheſt glory, nor to that fulneſs of joy, which they ſhall enter into at the Reſurrection, when they ſhall be re-united to their bodies, and ſo both together ſhall be taken into the everlaſting habitations, and ſhall ſtand in the preſence of God, and enjoy the beatificall Viſion, in whoſe light they ſhall ſee light, when they ſhall ſee God face to face, in whoſe preſence is fulneſs of joy, and at whoſe right hand there are pleaſures for evermore. This the Royall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet by his ſpirit of Propheſie foreſaw long agoe, and rejoyced under the hope of it, <hi>Pſal</hi> 17.15. <hi>I ſhall behold thy face in righteouſneſs: and when I awake, I ſhall be ſatisfied with thy Image:</hi> When I awake, that is, in the morning of the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then I ſhall be ſatisfied with thine Image, then, and not till then, ſhall I be fully ſatisfied with thine Image.</p>
               <p>But then here ariſeth another Queſtion, as there did of the ſouls of wicked men, <hi>Where are the ſouls of the juſt in the mean while, between the time of their ſeparation from the body by death, and the re-union of them with the body at the Reſurrection? Where are they? What becomes of them? In what ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition have they their being? What is their imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? What is their enjoyments?</hi> To all theſe foure
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:59533:48"/>Quaeries, I ſhall endeavour to give you ſome ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, as touching the Place, the State, the imployment, and the enjoyments of ſouls ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated.</p>
               <p>And as to the firſt of theſe, <hi>The place of the ſouls ſeparation.</hi> I ſhall not ſend you to the Ely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan fields of the antient Poëts to ſeek them: Nor to the Gardens nor Orchards of the <hi>Heſperides:</hi> Nor to the <hi>Mahometan Paradiſes;</hi> all theſe concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and beleeved, <hi>That the ſouls of vertuous and juſt men, as ſoon as they were ſeparated from the body, did paſs into ſome place of reſt and joy,</hi> wherein they were not deceived; but for want of a more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct knowledge of the Place where they had their being, and their ſtate in it, they ſet it forth by comparing it to the being in thoſe places which they conceived to be moſt happy, pleaſant, and joyous. But certainly, that which is moſt agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to reaſon in this caſe, and is no way repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to any Article of Faith, nor to any diſcovery in Scripture made to the contrary, is this, That the ſouls of the juſt being ſeparated from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, doe paſs into thoſe high Heavens which are above the Starry Firmament, as the ſouls of wicked men doe paſs into the Regions of the Aire below it. For that there are Heavens above the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:59533:49"/>Starry Firmament, it cannot be denyed: two we reade of before we come to the Empyrean Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, where the Throne of God is, and where the Lord of Hoſts, with all his holy Angells keeps his Court in Majeſty and Glory: The lower-moſt of theſe is called, <hi>Caelum aqueum,</hi> The watery Heaven, from the clearneſs, and the tranſparancy of it: The other above that is called, <hi>Caelum Cryſtallinum,</hi> The Cryſtall Heaven, from the purity, and the pellu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidity of it, for ſtill the higher the Heavens are, and the neerer they approach to the Empyrean Heaven, where the Throne of God is, the more glorious are they, and the more noble the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of them. Now between every of theſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, there is a vaſt ſpace of infinite capacity; and it muſt needs be ſo, by reaſon of the greatneſs of their circumference, the leaſt and loweſt of them is of greater capacity and comprehenſion, then all this ſpace that is between the Earth and the Starry Firmament, and the reſt greater then it proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onably. Now I would ask, <hi>Of what uſe theſe vaſt and comprehenſive Heavens are, if this be not one, to be the receptacle of the ſouls of the juſt, when they are taken out of their bodies?</hi> Natura nihil facit fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrà, <hi>The God of Nature, the Creator of all things, hath made nothing in vain:</hi> There is no part of the world
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:59533:49"/>which he hath made, but he hath ſtor'd, and ſtock't it with Inhabitants ſuitable to it: The Earth he hath ſtor'd and ſtock't with Beaſts and Cattell; the Sea with Fiſhes, the Ayre with Fowle, and with Aeriall Inhabitants; every of the Spheres above it, with Starrs and Planets, which by their light, heare, influence, and motion divide the times, and Governe this inferiour world: The Starry Firmament that is ſpread out as a vaile be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this inferiour, and the ſuperiour world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe lower and the higher Heavens, it is peopled (as it were) with innumerable Golden Starrs of ſeverall magnitudes, ſpecious to behold, and pretious for their uſe and influence: The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyrean Heavens, the higheſt of all the reſt, is ſtor'd and Inhabited with Angells, and Arch-An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells, Cherubims, and Seraphims, and the other Orders of thoſe Heavenly Courtiers that ſtand in the preſence of God, waiting his pleaſure, and ready to execute his will, and to fulfill his Word: Thus the whole Univerſe is repleniſhed with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants ſuitable to the places which the Great Creator and high diſpoſer of all things hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for them. And doe theſe beautifull Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, the <hi>Aqueall</hi> and <hi>Chryſtalline</hi> Heavens, ſo ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ſo ſpacious between the Starry Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:59533:50"/>and the Empyrean Heaven, ſtand voyd and empty without Inhabitants? No, it cannot be, but they have their Inhabitants too, and <hi>they are the ſouls of the Juſt, when they are ſeparated from their bodies by death and diſſolution, who being next un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Angells in holineſs, are placed in receptacles next unto them in glory.</hi> The <hi>Chryſtalline</hi> Heaven next and immediately under the <hi>Empyrean</hi> Heaven; and the <hi>Aqueall,</hi> or <hi>Watry</hi> Heaven next immediately under it; and as they have atteined to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of purity here in this life, ſo are they diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of into the one, or into the other of them, neerer or farther off from the Throne of glory; for as after the Reſurrection, there ſhall be ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and different degrees of glory; ſo in this ſtate of ſeparation, the ſouls ſeparated, ſhall be in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and different degrees of joy and happineſs, according as they are prepared for it, and have atteined to ſeverall degrees of holineſs and purity in this life, while they were in the body.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>If you enquire into the ſtate of thoſe ſouls ſeparated, it muſt needs be bleſſed and glorious, ſuitable to the glory of thoſe Heavens wherein they are?</hi> Where firſt, They are delivered from the burden of the Fleſh, the body, the very priſon wherein they were deteined, and ſole impediment of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:59533:50"/>Secondly, They are freed from all ſin, and ſorrow, concupiſcence and corruption, from all temptations and ſollicitations from the world, the devill, and the fleſh, and from all the evill of this lower world which they have left behind them; and which now, <hi>As that glorious Woman,</hi> Rev. 12.1. <hi>they trample under their feet, all tears are wipt from their eyes, all ſorrow, and grief, and pain are flowne away, they dyed in the Lord, they are bleſſed, they reſt from their labours, and ſo they are in</hi> Abraham's <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</hi> They are in the hand of God, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Wiſedom</hi> 3.1. <hi>ſo that no evill ſhall touch them;</hi> they are got above the reach of the malice of men or Devills, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (as the Greek Proverbe hath it) <hi>out of the danger of the dart:</hi> And ſo their ſtate agrees with that which St. <hi>John</hi> ſayes of them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. <hi>That he ſaw them under the Altar;</hi> yet all this is but their privative happineſs, conſiſting in their freedom from all evill, and their ſecurity from all danger; but they are in preſent poſſeſſion of a poſitive bleſſedneſs too in a great meaſure, and high degree of preſent joy and glory: Their very imployment is a part of their bleſſedneſs, which is no leſs then Angelicall, to laud, and prayſe, and magnifie the living Lord, to ſing <hi>Hoſanna</hi> to <hi>Hoſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi>'s <hi>in the higheſt,</hi> and <hi>Hallelujahs to him that ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:59533:51"/>upon the Threne;</hi> to admire the glory, and the greatneſs, and the goodneſs, and the power, and the holineſs of the mighty Lord God, of which they have now a clearer ſight and apprehenſion then before; and in particular, his ſingular, and unſpeakable grace and goodneſs unto them, which hath done ſuch great things for them, as to bring them thither to triumph in the apprehenſion of it, and to rejoyce and glory in the ſence of it. I know not whether I ſhould rather ranke theſe things under their imployments, or their enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they are bleſſed duties which are both: With what ſweet contentation, and ſelfe ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction doe they converſe together in pure love and light? With what joy and comfort can they now remember the difficulties, and the dangers which they have paſt through in their comming thither? What temptations? what afflictions they have met withall? What ſtrong corruptions they have wreſtled with? What importunate luſts they have denied and ſubdued? What ſollicitations from the World, from the Fleſh, and from the Devill, they have reſiſted and rejected, and how now they bleſs themſelves that they have done ſo, and God that gave them grace and ſtrength to doe it? With what joy and prayſe doe they congratulate
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:59533:51"/>one another in their happy victories over ſin and Satan, Death and Hell, and all the enemies of their ſalvation, and in their ſafe paſſage through all the dangers and difficulties that ſtood between them and Heaven; and that having eſcaped all the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption that is in the world through Luſt, they are at length arrived to the Place where they would, even to the top of Mount <hi>Syon,</hi> the Place of their reſt and joy, where now they are taken into neerer Communion with God, then they could be, before they have more clear manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him, ſweet influences from him, and union with him; they converſe with Angels, congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating them in their happineſs, and with <hi>Euges</hi> of joy and prayſe, well-coming them into thoſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, the habitations of their happineſs, the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of their joy and glory. And now, their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity invites them to Pray <hi>for the whole eſtate of Chriſts Church militant here on Earth, That the Lord would guide them, and keep them in the way of Truth, that he would bring them ſafe through all the dangers and difficulties that ſtand in the way between them and Heaven; that the Goſpel may have free paſſage through the world; that it may runne, proſper, and be glorious; that by it, he would call in all that are yet uncalled; that he would ſhortly accompliſh the number of his
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:59533:52"/>elect, and haſten his Kingdom; that they with them, and all others that ſhall depart out of this life in the faith and feare of his holy Name, may have their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect conſummation, and bliſs, both in body and ſoule in his eternall and everlaſting glory:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which is the third eſtate, in which immortall ſouls doe paſs their immortality, which begins from the day of the generall Judgement, and laſts from thence to all eternity.</p>
               <p>Of which, though we had the Tongue of Men, or Angells, it is impoſſible to ſpeak to the full, and as the ſubject requires: <hi>O Aeternity, Aeternity, How is the Heart aſtoniſh't, and the Mind ſwallowed up, that enters into the thoughts of it!</hi> with the ſtate of the juſt, and the unjuſt in it; the joy and glory of the one, and the miſery and torment of the other: both which being unexpreſſible, I ſhall forbeare to enter into the deſcription of them, and in ſtead thereof, onely referr you to the words of the ſentences at the great day to be given upon them both; the ſentence of abſolution to the juſt on the right hand, and of condemnation to the wicked on the left, both which the Judge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that ſhall pronounce them, hath told us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand, and left us <hi>in terminis</hi> upon record, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:59533:52"/>
               <p> And firſt, The ſentence of abſolution, becauſe that ſhall be firſt pronounc'c, that the wicked on the left hand may ſee Heaven opened, and have a ſight of the joy and glory of the Celeſtiall Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, and ſee the juſt taken into it, and ſet down with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob in the Kingdom of Heaven, and themſelves caſt out;</hi> that they may ſee what happineſs they have loſt, by wilfully for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking their own mercy, and putting from them the Kingdom of Heaven offered unto them; and what happineſs, joy, and glory the ſervants of God are arrived unto, whom they deſpiſed, to the greater aggravation of their ſorrow and miſery: Therefore ſhall the ſentence of Abſolution be firſt pronounc't in theſe comfortable words, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father, enter into the Inheritance of the Kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world:</hi> Every word carries in it life and glory: <hi>Come ye bleſſed ones, take poſſeſſion of a Kingdom;</hi> Who? and what are we, that the Lord ſhould doe ſo much for us (may they well ſay) as to give us a Kingdom? That's the day of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> tells them, <hi>Jeſus Christ ſhall be admired in all them that beleeve,</hi> 2 Theſ. 1.10. not onely by them, but in them, by Men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells, to ſee that the Lord hath exalted his poor,
<pb facs="tcp:59533:53"/>humble, and deſpicable ſervants to ſo high ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, that he hath brought them hitherto: <hi>Then ſhall the righteous ſhine as the Sunne in his bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> (Wiſedom 5.1, 2, 3, 4.) <hi>in the Kingdom of their Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this ſhall the Judge turne himſelfe to the wicked, on the left hand, and pronounce againſt them the ſentence of condemnation, in theſe words, <hi>Ite maledicti, Goe ye curſed into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devill and his Angels:</hi> Every word full of death and terror; <hi>Goe,</hi> and <hi>goe ye curſed,</hi> and <hi>goe into fire,</hi> and <hi>fire everlaſting,</hi> and <hi>fire prepared,</hi> (Iſay 30.33.) <hi>and prepared for the Devill and his Angels: ſo theſe ſhall goe into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting torments, and the righteous into life eternall.</hi> And this is the third eſtate of of immortall ſouls, and in this they ſhall abide for ever, without alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, without end. And ſo I end my Diſcourſe upon this Subject, in which, I may truely ſay with <hi>Moſes, I have ſet before you life and death, bleſſing and curſing, Heaven and Hell,</hi> that ſo you may chuſe the better, and that you may doe it in time, while remedy may be had, <hi>That you may live, and not dye; that you may be bleſſed, and not curſed; that your Portion may be in Heaven, and not in Hell,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:59533:53"/>
               <p> IT teſts now, that I ſhould ſpeak ſomething <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the third part of the Text, in theſe words.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For I am no better then my Fathers.</head>
               <p>But an intervenient occaſion makes me inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a few Lines for the ſatisfaction of ſome, of whom I heare they ſhould ſay, <hi>That in the former Diſcourſe concerning the ſtate of ſouls ſeparated from their bodies, I Preach't New Doctrine; And ask't whereunto is was uſefull?</hi> Which exception hath two parts in it: The firſt, Concerning the new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it. And the ſecond, Concerning the uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs of it. To both which I muſt ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in way of vindication. And as to the firſt, <hi>The newneſs of it,</hi> To paſs by all that hath been Written by the Learned Schoolemen, of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> perſwaſion, becauſe they were of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> perſwaſion, (and yet, if we ſhould reject all that is written by the learned of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe they were of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> perſwaſion) we ſhall doe our ſelves as much wrong as them; but to wave them, I could fill up my Page with the teſtimonies of Learned, and holy men unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptionable, which have declared themſelves of the ſame Judgement in this matter, That neither the ſouls of the juſt, nor the unjuſt, doe immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately upon the ſeparation of them from the body,
<pb facs="tcp:59533:54"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſtate of their ternall being, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſtate intermediate, and different from the third ſtate, at leaſt in degree, in which they doe remain untill the Reſurrection, and the generall Judgement: The one in Priſon, the other in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe: The one amongſt the evill Angells, the other among the good Angells: The one in the mouth of Hell it ſelfe, and in the beginnings of woe and torment in a great degree, and the other in the very entrance into the higheſt Heaven in bliſs and joy, and happineſs unſpeakable, and glorious. I ſhould make a long buſineſs of it here to cite, and to recite the teſtimonies of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents in this matter; but to ſave my ſelfe and Reader that labour, let me intreat him to conſult the Writings of an eminent Divine, well known and approved of in the Evangelicall Churches for Learned and Orthodox, and Profeſſor of Divinity in the Univerſity of <hi>Lauſanna,</hi> I meane <hi>Bucanus,</hi> a man as directly oppoſit to Purgatory and Popery, as Light is to Darkneſs, in his Common Places, <hi>Loc.</hi> 39 under the Title, <hi>De Vita aeterna,</hi> he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes this very Queſtion in theſe words. Firſt of the ſouls of the faithfull;</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Anne anunae piorum nunc a corporibus ſeparate perfecta, &amp; tonſummata beatitudine fruantur?</hi>
               </q>
               <pb facs="tcp:59533:54"/>
               <p> Whether the ſouls of the faithfull ſeparated from their bodies, doe preſently enjoy perfect bliſs, and conſummate happineſs.</p>
               <p>Unto which he makes this Anſwer:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Satis ſit nobis ſcire illicô à diſceſſu è corpore, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum redire ad Deum, qui dedit illum,</hi> Eccleſ. 12.7. <hi>Eſſe cum Chriſto,</hi> Philip. 1.23. <hi>In Paradiſo,</hi> Luke 23.43. <hi>In pace,</hi> Sapien. 3.3. <hi>In requie,</hi> Heb. 4.3. <hi>In conſolatione,</hi> Luke 16.25. <hi>In refrigerio,</hi> Sap. 4.7. <hi>In ſecuritate,</hi> Job 11.15. <hi>In manu Dei, ut minime at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingit eum cruciatus,</hi> Sapien. 3.1. <hi>In glorificatione,</hi> Wiſd. 5.1. <hi>Thus Engliſhed:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let it be enough for us to know, That preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the departure of it out of the body, the ſpirit returns to God that gave it; that it is with Chriſt, that it is in Paradiſe, that it is in Peace, in reſt, in comfort, in a place of refreſhment, in ſecurity, in the hand of God, ſo that no evill ſhall touch it; that it is in glory, all glorious expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſetting forth the happy ſtate of the ſouls of the Saints which they paſs into, preſently upon the ſeparation of them from the bodies. But then, marke what follows, he comes in upon all this with an <hi>adverſitive tamen,</hi> notwithſtanding, which in anſwer to the Queſtion here propoſed, hath the force of a negative, for thus it followeth;</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:59533:55"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Quia tamen reſurrectionem corporum expectant, &amp; fruitionem pleniſſimam omnium bonorum quae Deus promiſit diligentibus ipſum, non in perfecta, &amp; jam conſummata, ſed inchoata beatitudine verſari dici poſſunt. Engliſhed thus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet notwithſtanding, becauſe they expect the reſurrection of their bodies, and the moſt full fruition of all thoſe good things, which God hath promiſed to them that love him, they may be ſaid to be not in the full fruition of their perfect and conſummate happineſs, but in the beginning of it, or their happineſs inchoated; and begun. Thus <hi>Bucanus Com. Loc.</hi> 39. <hi>pag.</hi> 447.</p>
               <p>And for proofe of this, he alleageth the ſame Text of Scripture, that I have done, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.9, 10, 11. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſque quo Domine? How long Lord, how long?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aquinas</hi> brings in a another Scripture for proofe of this truth, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. <hi>From henceforth is layd up for me a Crowne of righteouſneſs, which the Lord the righteous Judge ſhall give unto me at that day.</hi> At what day? At the day of his glorious appearing, as it follows in the ſame Text, <hi>When Chriſt ſhall appear in flaming fire to render vengeance.</hi> 2 Theſ. 1.7. <hi>When the Sonne of Man ſhall come in the Clouds, with power and great glory, and all his holy Angels with him:</hi> That's the day of his appearing; at that
<pb facs="tcp:59533:55"/>day ſhall St. <hi>Paul</hi> receive his <hi>Crowne,</hi> not before; till then, it is layd up for him. At that day ſhall thoſe ſouls under the Altar, before mentioned, receive their Crowns of Martyrdome alſo; for the preſent, there were <hi>white Robes given</hi> to every one of them; but not the <hi>Crowns till that day.</hi> The ſame alſo doth he affirme of the ſtate of the ſouls of wicked men ſeparated from their bodies; <hi>Sic puniri ut etiam reſerventur in diem judicii longe aliis aſperioribus paenis aeternis, videlicet, in corpore, &amp; anima cruciandi:</hi> That they are ſo puniſhed here, during the time of their ſeparation, that they are alſo reſerved unto the Judgement of the great day, then to be tormented in body and ſoul with farr more ſharp and grievous puniſhments for evermore.</p>
               <p>But if you would ſee more of Antiquity in theſe matters, and will be at the pains of it, doe but conſult <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> in an Epiſtle of his, cited by <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> Haereſ. 77. and in his Book, <hi>De Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione Verbi.</hi> St. <hi>Cyrill, De r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ta ſide ad Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſium. Oe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cumenius,</hi> and divers others, who in their Expoſitions of that Text in St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Who was put to death as concerning the Fleſh, but quickned by the Spirit. By which Spirit, he went and Preach't to the ſpirits which are in Priſon.</hi> We
<pb facs="tcp:59533:56"/>prove firſt, Chriſts deſcent into Hell; and upon the words following, That he Preach't unto the ſpirits, or ſouls detained in that Priſon. As Saint <hi>Jude</hi> ſaith of the evill Angells, <hi>That they are in priſon, and bound in chains of darkneſs, reſerved unto the judgement of the great day:</hi> The evill Angells, and the ſouls of wicked men, both in the ſame condition, both ſecur'd in Priſon, both in chains, both reſerv'd unto the judgement of the great day: And it will follow by the rule of oppoſits, That if the ſouls of the Saints and Martyrs be not yet in the fruition of their perfect and conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate happineſs; then neither are the ſouls of wicked men in that exquiſite torment, which they are condemned unto, and into which they ſhall be caſt at the judgement of the great day: but that there is an intermediate eſtate, though that very wretched and miſerable, under which they lye, untill that day: And, I think, this is ſufficiently proved in both the branches of it by Scriptures, ſtrong and cleere for it, and by the jugdements of holy and learned men, commenting upon them; and ſo is a ſufficient anſwer to the firſt Part of the exception, and enough to free me from Preaching <hi>New Doctrine,</hi> and to declare that I am not alone in this Opinion, Of the intermediate eſtate of
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:59533:56"/>ſouls ſeparated from the body, both of the juſt, and the unjuſt, nor walk in an untroden path, where no foot is gone before me.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Part of the exception lyes in this, <hi>That it is uſeleſs:</hi> That admitting theſe tenents be true, yet they are uſeleſs: It demands therefore <hi>Whereto they are uſefull?</hi> To which I Anſwer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> The knowledge of them is uſefull to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſpeciall purpoſes; particularly to theſe:</p>
               <p>Firſt, It is very ſatisfactory to the minde of every man (I think) that hath a ſoule, to know the ſtate of it, both preſent and future; yea, to know as much of it, as is knowable: Knowledge is pretious, and a great delight unto the ſoule; <hi>When wiſedom entreth into thy heart, and knowledge delighteth thy ſoule,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, Prov,</hi> 2.10. So knowledge is a delight unto the ſoule, and the more high and excellent the object is, about which it is converſant, the more excellent and pretious is the knowledge. But what more high and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious object can there be, next unto God, and the Angells, then the ſpirits and ſouls of men? What more worthy to take up our moſt ſerious thoughts, and diligent ſtudies, then the diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of thoſe high things that doe concerne them? What more ſatisfactory then the attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:59533:57"/>of them in all thoſe things that are know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
               <p>Secondly, 'Tis uſefull for preſerving of men againſt Atheiſme, that bruitiſh ſinne, which doth ſo ſpread it ſelfe in the world, and invaded ſo great a part of the Sonns of men; for though they doe not ſpeak out plainly with their Tongues, yet how many of them ſay in their hearts and lives, <hi>There is no God, nor Devill, nor Heaven, nor Hell, nor An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells, nor Spirits, nor ſouls of Men?</hi> and all through their ignorance of this Point, That they cannot ſatisfie themſelves what becomes of the ſouls of men ſeparated from their bodies, through ſo long a tract of time as two, three, foure, or five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years intermediate between the time of their diſſolution by Death, and their re-union again at the Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, 'Tis uſefull to confirme men in the aſſurance of the Immortality of the ſoule, while it informes them what becomes of it, where it is, and what it does or ſuffers, where is the place of it, what the ſtate of it, what the imployments, what the enjoyments: Concerning all which, being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ignorant, and in the dark, they could not tell what to think of the ſouls of men, more then of bruits, of which <hi>Solomon</hi> takes notice, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.20,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:59533:57"/>21. ſpeaking in their Language, <hi>Who knoweth whether the ſpirit of Man aſcend upward? and the ſpirit of a Beaſt deſcend downward? All goe to one place, &amp;c.</hi> and therefore rann away in their own fancies, and vain imaginations, into divers errors, concerning the ſouls of men dying; ſome ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining they were annihilated, and altogether ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed: Some, that they were layd aſleep, as the bodies were, till the Reſurrection: Some, that they were tranſmigrated out of one body into another: Some one thing, ſome another; in the midſt of theſe doubtfull varieties, they began to queſtion, whether there were any difference between the ſouls of men, and of bruits, as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> here intimates; and for want of ſome more diſtinct knowledge in this matter, lived at a ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Againſt all theſe errors and evills, the truths here delivered are a ſure and ſoveraigne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy; the vain imaginations in which men rann away in the variety of their own fancies, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the extinction, annihilation, ſleeping, tranſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gration, &amp;c. of the ſouls of men dying, all dye before theſe truths here delivered, and vaniſh away, and mens minds are ſetled and confirmed in the aſſurance of the immortality of the ſouls, while they doe diſtinctly informe them, what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes
<pb facs="tcp:59533:58"/>comes of them, into what receptacles they are received upon their ſeparation, and in what ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſtates they paſs their immortality.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, It is uſefull for admoniſhing of all men while they are in the body, to take care of their ſouls, and to provide for their future condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to preſerve them pure, that upon their ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, they may be taken up into thoſe pure ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations, into which no unclean thing may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, not to defile, or clog them with ſinne and guilt, whereby they may be preſt down, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in their flight and paſſage into the higher Heavens, the glorious receptacles appointed for them.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, It is uſefull for the overthrowing of that <hi>Limbus Patrum, Limbus Infantum,</hi> and other roomes and ſpacious places in the Fabricke of the Popiſh Purgatory, which they have erected in their own imaginations for receptacles, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they would lodge the ſouls of men, when they are ſeparated from their bodies, there to remain for a long tract of time in priſon, and in pain, till they be ſufficiently purged and puniſhed, except there be ſome extraordinary means uſed for the reliefe, or releaſe of them, or for the mitigating of their paine, either firſt, by a multitude of Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:59533:58"/>dayly ſaid and ſung for them. Or ſecondly, By the ſuffrages of the living, praying for the dead, from whence all theſe Epitaphs upon their Graves and Tombes, <hi>Orate pro animâ,</hi> Pray for the ſoule of ſuch a one. Or thirdly, By ſome munificence, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent works of Charity done upon their account. Or fourthly, By applying unto them ſome of the works of <hi>ſupererogation,</hi> taken out of the Treaſury of the Church, and by the Popes ſpecial favour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd upon them, &amp;c. Theſe imaginations (before the truth in this Diſcourſe declared) fall to the ground, while it teacheth, That there is no ſuch <hi>Limbus Patrum</hi> as they pretend to, nor need there any; but that their ſouls preſently upon the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of them, paſs into the Etheriall Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, where they are in reſt, and peace, in bliſs, happineſs and glory, <hi>that the blood of Chriſt ſhed in due time, that was in the fulneſs of time,</hi> was as effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall to the purging, waſhing, ſaving, and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the ſouls of the Fathers that lived in the firſt generation of the world, before his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the fleſh, as it is now, for the purging, waſhing, ſaving and ſanctifying of the ſouls of beleevers ſince his coming, and will be to the end of the world, that as to the vertue of his Death, Paſſion, Reſurrection, and Aſcenſion, <hi>He was a
<pb facs="tcp:59533:59"/>Lambe ſlaine from the beginning of the world, and whoſe going out have been from the beginning, and from everlaſting,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Micah</hi> tells us; and as the Apoſtle declares him, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, It is uſefull for the anſwering of that great queſtion, with which we are ſo frequently, and ſo importunately urged by inquiſitive peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to ſhew them, <hi>where Locall Hell is:</hi> They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſatisfie themſelves where Locall Hell is; and therefore they are apt to beleeve, there is none at all: This Diſcourſe ſatisfies them where it is; for the preſent, it is <hi>where the evill Angells are confin'd, and ſecur'd in chains of darkneſs.</hi> It is <hi>where the ſouls of wicked men are impriſoned, both reſerved to the Judgement of the great day:</hi> And where that is, this Diſcourſe tells; and not this Diſcourſe, or Treatiſe, but the Apoſtle St. <hi>Jude, ver.</hi> 6. St. <hi>Paul, Epheſ.</hi> 6.12. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.2. St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.19. Thoſe places where thoſe evill Angells, and where the ſouls and ſpirits of wicked men are impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ſecured untill that day, are the Locall Hell for the preſent. If you ask further, <hi>Where Locall Hell ſhall be, after that great day?</hi> I Anſwer, What need you look any further for it, then the vaſt ſpace conteining this wretched and wicked
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:59533:59"/>inferiour world wherein we now dwell. You know what St. <hi>Peter</hi> hath Propheſied concerning it, with all the Elements in it, all the Creatures, and works upon it, all the viſible Heavens over it, that they ſhall be conſumed by fire, 2 <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 3.10. <hi>The Heavens ſhall paſs away with a noyſe, and the Elements ſhall melt with fervent heat, and the Earth, with the works therein ſhall be conſumed by fire:</hi> Now, when theſe things ſhall be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, conſumed, annihilated, what need we look any further for a Locall Hell then this vaſt ſpace which theſe mighty bodies took up, when they were in being? When there ſhall be no Sunne to rule the day, nor Moon, nor Starrs to govern the Night, nor to divide the times; there ſhall be no diſtinction between day and night, but all ſhall be night without day, when the Sunne ſhall be no more, the Sea ſhall be no more, time ſhall be no more, the Earth ſhall be no more, all theſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Heavens within the reach of the conflagra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be no more, there's ſpace enough for the Locall Hell ſo much enquired after. I have deſcribed to you before the preſent Hell, the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in which the evill Angells, and ſouls of wicked men with them are ſecur'd unto that day, and ſo are already in the beginnings of that Hell
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:59533:60"/>
                  <hi>kept for fire; they ſhall be burnt up; they ſhall paſs away with a great noyſe, melt with fervent heat, be diſſolved;</hi> and all this while, and amongſt them all, not one word of purgation, purifying, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining, or reſerving the ſubſtance of it: It is clear, St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf ſpeaks not of a <hi>refining,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the qualities; but an utter abolition of the ſubſtance it ſelfe of this old world: As the Pageant being finiſhed, the Stage is taken away; ſo all the Tragedies which are Acted upon the Stage of this world, being ended, the Stage ſhall be pulled down, broken in pieces, burnt with fire, as an Engine or Fabrick of which there is no more uſe, it ſhall be no more.</p>
               <p>But what ſhall we ſay to the other Objection, rayſed out of the words of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> ver. 13. <hi>But we look for new Heavens, and a new Earth, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his promiſe, wherein dwelleth righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which words ſeem to import, That though this preſent old World ſhall then be diſſolved, conſumed, burnt up; yet (if there doe not ſpring up (as a Phoenix) out of the Aſhes of it another World, yet) God will Create another new World in the room of it, and then we are but where we were, in reſpect of the ſpace, and place, and room
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:59533:60"/>we ſhould have for Locall Hell, theſe new Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and Earth will take it up.</p>
               <p>To this I Anſwer, That indeed, we doe look for <hi>new Heavens, and a new Earth,</hi> according to his promiſe, and according to St. <hi>Peters</hi> words, and ſhall enjoy them too, and dwell in them. But what are thoſe Heavens? but thoſe higheſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, the Celeſtiall Paradiſe, the glorious habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the Saints, and of Gods Elect, which he hath prepared for them from the beginning of the world, and into which he will receive them at that day, when he ſhall ſay unto them, <hi>Venite benedicti: Come ye bleſſed, enter into the Kingdom prepared for you from the beginning of the world:</hi> and theſe are called <hi>New;</hi> not in reſpect of their new making, but in reſpect of our new taking poſſeſſion of them (by a moſt happy change) for our new habitations: So that, New Heavens, and New Earth, in this place ſignifieth no more, but a New Habitation, farr more glorious then this that we now have in this lower world; that as now, the Earth under us, and the Heavens over us, are the place of our Habitation; ſo, after theſe ſhall be deſtroyed, that we may not fear we ſhall want a habitation, he tells us, We ſhall have another, and a better Habitation, farr more excellent and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:59533:61"/>glorious then this is, which in alluſion to theſe, he calls, New Heavens, and New Earth, to make us know, we ſhall be no loſers by the change: And for this expoſition, I might quote you Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors enough, <hi>Ireneus, Hilary, Hypolitus,</hi> and others; but I will cite you a whole Library of Fathers and Schoolemen, and all in one, who was him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a living Library, I meane the late Learned and Reverend Lord Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi> Doctor <hi>Prideaux, Regius Profeſſor</hi> in the Univerſity of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and <hi>Rector</hi> of <hi>Exeter Colledge,</hi> in which I lived under his Government ſome years: He Preach't at the Court upon this very Text, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 3.13. his Sermon is in Print, and intitled, <hi>The Chriſtians ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation;</hi> where all along, he proves, <hi>The New Heavens,</hi> here mentioned, to be no other, <hi>but the higheſt Heavens,</hi> appointed for the Habitations of the Saints in glory.</p>
               <p>But what need we trouble our ſelves to ſearch the Libraries of the Fathers and Schoolemen, to ask their Judgement and Conſent in this matter? St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe has cleered the Point in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to our hands, That <hi>the Heavens,</hi> in the Text, though here called <hi>New,</hi> can be no other, but thoſe glorious Heavens above, now in being: For thus he further commendeth them to us, <hi>That
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:59533:61"/>they are Heavens wherein dwelleth righteouſneſs:</hi> he doth not ſay, <hi>wherein ſhall dwell righteouſneſs,</hi> in the future; but <hi>wherein now dwelleth righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> in the preſent Tenſe. We cannot ſay of Heavens hereafter to be Created, That righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs now dwelleth in them, before they are in being: But the Apoſtle ſaith expreſsly of the Heavens which we look for, <hi>That righteouſneſs now dwelleth in them,</hi> therefore they are now in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, long ſince Created from the beginning. That which is in expectation, and the newneſs here mentioned, is not to be underſtood in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the making of them, or the future be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, as if they were not yet in being; but in reſpect of our entrance into them, our taking Poſſeſſion of them, and Habitation in them, ſo they ſhall be new to us. I know there are of the other Opinion, not a few, for the new Creation of a new World, new Heavens, and a new Earth in the roome of this preſent World, when it ſhall be aboliſht and diſſolved: But ſee how weakly they proſecute that fancy, when they would confirme themſelves, and others in it: They tell us of what excellent uſe it ſhall be; As firſt, For a Monument of what hath been. Secondly, For a receptacle of ſuch as had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:59533:62"/>neither Heaven nor Hell; ſuch as they thought were not capable of the one, and they thought it pitty they ſhould be condemned to the other; ſuch as Infants, dying without Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, Idiots, and ignorant people, that wanted capacity to underſtand the truth; honeſt morall men, which never had the way of Goſpel-ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made known unto them, ſuch as <hi>Plato, Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle, Plutarch, Cato, &amp;c.</hi> Thirdly, That it might be an out-let, or as it were, a Country Houſe for the Saints and Angells to come down into, where to ſolace themſelves for their recreation, and the like; all but <hi>Rabbinicall</hi> fancies, and <hi>Jeſuiticall</hi> ſurmiſes, without any ground any where, but in their own imaginations: As if the Lord had not roome enough wherein to diſpoſe of his Saints and Angells, and all his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, except he ſhould make another new World to entertein them in. Whereas our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our tells us, <hi>Their receptacles were prepared for them from the beginning of the world,</hi> Mat. 25. <hi>Known to the Lord are all his works from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning;</hi> and he will not have ſo many ſupernu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meraries in the end of the World, as that the Fabrick made in the beginning for the reception of them, ſhould not ſerve the turne. But to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:59533:62"/>the doubtfull in this ſcruple, let it be well minded what St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith further here in this Text, <hi>We look for new Heavens,</hi> not for a new Heaven, in the ſingular; but <hi>for new Heavens,</hi> in the Plurall number: By which it appears, there are more Heavens then one in the World above, for the Lord to diſpoſe of his Saints and Angells in; a juſtification to what I have ſaid in the former Part of this Treatiſe, wherein I affirmed, That there are more Heavens then one above the Starry Firmament. I named two between it, and the Empyrean, or fiery Heaven, where the Throne of God is; and who knows how many more there may be? Let no man object againſt this, what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes of his <hi>Rapture into the third Heaven,</hi> and therefore there are no more; that doth not follow, A man is taken up into a third place,; therefore there is not a fourth, nor a fifth: It would follow rather the contrary, that there were: For, <hi>Non dicitur primus niſi in ordine ad ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum:</hi> A firſt is not ſaid to be ſo, but in order to a ſecond, and ſo forward; <hi>In numeris ordinalibus,</hi> in numbers of order, till you come to the laſt. I ſay farther, that in ſuch accounts, a reſpect is to be had where you begin to number, according to which the ſame place may fall in account to be
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:59533:63"/>firſt, or ſecond, or third, or fourth. Thirdly, The Heavens are ſaid to be more, or leſs, as they are diſtinguiſhed and divided. So <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> numbers but eight, <hi>Ptolomie</hi> nine, <hi>Purbacchius</hi> ten, <hi>Maginus</hi> eleven, and this diſtinction they make from the diſtinct motions they have obſerved in the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring and fixed Starrs. Our Chriſtian Divines generally number but three, and that from Saint <hi>Pauls rapture,</hi> mentioned before: Yet a Reverend and Learned Biſhop of ours, I mean Biſhop <hi>Bilſon,</hi> in his Survey of <hi>Chriſts ſufferings,</hi> numbers foure, and that fourth to be that which is called, <hi>The Heaven of Heavens:</hi> For, <hi>That Chriſt is ſaid to have aſcended farr above all Heavens,</hi> Epheſ. 4.10.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee here are great varieties of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions touching the number of the Heavens, and the Celeſtiall Orbs: And yet in the midſt of all this variety, the difference is not ſo great, but it may be fairly reconciled, ſo as there ſhall be found no contradiction at all betwixt them: as thus, Be they as many as they will, they may all conveniently be divided, or ſorted into theſe three Heavens, or compages of Heavens (if you will:) The Aëriall, the Sydereall, and the Ethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Heavens: Under the firſt of theſe is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:59533:63"/>all that ſpace, which from the Earth upwards, reacheth unto the Moone, the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of the Luminaries of Heaven, Foules fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in it, are called, <hi>Foules of Heaven,</hi> Mat. 6.26. Under the ſecond is comprehended all thoſe Orbes and Sphears wherein the Starrs are placed, whether the fixed, or the wandering Starrs: The Starrs are called, <hi>Starrs of Heaven.</hi> And under the third is comprehended all that infinite ſpace, which is above the Starry Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Sydereall Heavens, be it never ſo great, or the Heavens in it never ſo many; and ſo in this three-fold diviſion of the Heavens, into Aëriall, Sydereall, and Etheriall, we ſhall eaſily reconcile Aſtronomy and Divinity toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Mathematicall Account, with the Theologicall. In it St. <hi>Paul</hi> may finde <hi>his third Heaven,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi> his fourth, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> may finde his eight, <hi>Ptolomy</hi> his nines, <hi>Purbacchius</hi> his tenn, and <hi>Maginus</hi> his eleven, and neither of them wrong other in the reckoning, ſo they ſeek them while they are there in being; but that muſt be before the Conflagration here in this Text Propheſied of by St. <hi>Peter.</hi> For in the great burning here ſpoken of, the two former, the Aëriall, and the Sydereall Heavens, with
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:59533:64"/>the whole compages of them, will be deſtroyed, burnt up, diſſolved, they all fall under the fury of the Conflagration. St. <hi>Peter</hi> hath expreſt the manner of it in tragicall expreſſions, filling the heart with terror and aſtoniſhment to think on: The burning of a Houſe, a Towne, a City, is a lamentable ſight. At the burning of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> and the Temple, <hi>Titus</hi> himſelf, which was the executioner of it, lamented greatly, and was ſore grieved, and troubled at ſo lamentable a ſpectacle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: But what was that, in compariſon to this, not ſo much as the burning of a Cottage in compariſon of it ſelfe? The burning of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah, Admah,</hi> and <hi>Zeboim,</hi> foure Cities in the Plaine, with fire and brimſtone from Heaven, was a Type of this burning, but ſlenderly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting it, as ſo many bonfires to a mighty burning. The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> fore-telling the horrible deſtruction of the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows it forth under the type and title of <hi>Tophet,</hi> or <hi>Hell, Iſay</hi> 30.33. in terrible termes as before remembred, <hi>For Tophet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> prepared of old: yea, even for the King it is prepared,</hi> (meaning the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> which in his cloſe ſiege againſt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> lay there with his Army, and went off with the loſs of one hundred foureſcore and five
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:59533:64"/>thouſand men) <hi>he hath made it deep and large: the pile thereof is fire, and much wood: the breath of the Lord, as a ſtreame of brunſtone, doth kindle it.</hi> This <hi>Tophet</hi> was a Valley on the South ſide of <hi>Jeruſalem, (Joſh.</hi> 18.16.) in which the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous <hi>Jews</hi> did burn their Children in the fire, <hi>to offer them up in ſacrifice unto</hi> Moloch, contrary to the expreſs command of God, <hi>Levit.</hi> 20.1. It was called <hi>Tophet,</hi> from <hi>Toph,</hi> which in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> ſignifieth <hi>a Drumme;</hi> from whence <hi>Tophet</hi> the diminutive of it ſignifying, <hi>a little Drumme,</hi> or <hi>Tabret;</hi> becauſe, while theſe Children were burning; the Idolatrous Prieſts beate upon theſe Drumms, and playd on theſe Tabrets, partly for the ſolemnity of the ſervice, and partly to drowne the crying, and ſhreeking of the poor In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents in the flames: It was the Land of one <hi>Hinnom,</hi> therefore called, <hi>The Valley of</hi> Hinnom; and in the New Teſtament, <hi>Gehenna,</hi> and taken for Hell, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.9. <hi>Joſiah</hi> had ſuch indignation againſt this Idolatrous place, that in his great Reformation, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.10. He defiled it, he made it the very ſinke, and dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill of the City, a place for the execution of Malefactors, and where thoſe which were denyed buriall, were caſt out, and lay unburied, a place
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:59533:65"/>where to carry and caſt all the noyſom Carrion of the City, where the Foules of the Ayre, and the beaſts might Prey upon them; yet, for feare they ſhould corrupt the Ayre, and cauſe infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſeaſes, there were continuall fires kept all-wayes burning, to conſume the bones, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trified Carkaſſes, whether of men or beaſts, which were caſt out there: And for the loathſomneſs of the place, and the continuall burnings in it, it was called <hi>Gehenna, Hell,</hi> and <hi>Hell fire:</hi> Unto which, it is probable, our Saviour alludes, when deſcribing <hi>Hell,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>The Worme never dyes, nor the Fire never goeth out:</hi> The <hi>Worme</hi> that is bred out of thoſe putrefactions, which farther gnawing, cauſeth farther putrefaction, never ceaſeth to adminiſter matter of burning to the fire, nor the fire ever goeth out, or ceaſeth to feed it ſelfe upon it: Yet, as there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers degrees of heate in the fire, and the fiery furnace into which the three Children were caſt, was heat <hi>ſeven times hotter, then at other times:</hi> So it is cleere by the Scriptures, <hi>That the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the damned, are not all equall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We reade of the Servant, <hi>That knew his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters wilt, and did it not:</hi> And of another, <hi>That knew it not, and did it not.</hi> The former was to
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:59533:65"/>be beaten with many ſtripes: The latter was to be beaten <hi>too, but</hi> with fewer ſtripes. The Stoicks were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rr out in their Moralls, when they taught; <hi>Peccata eſſe aequalia,</hi> That all ſinns were equall. Our Saviour his expoſition of the ſixth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, hath taught us otherwiſe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.22. when he ſaith, <hi>That whoſoever is angry with his brother unadviſedly, ſhall be in danger of the judgement: and whoſoever ſaith unto his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Racha, ſhall be worthy to be puniſhed by the Councell: but whoſoever ſhall ſay unto his brother, Thou foole, ſhall be in danger of Hell fire.</hi> Where under the forme of theſe three Courts among the <hi>Jews:</hi> Firſt, The Court of three, or the <hi>Triumviri,</hi> here called, <hi>The Judgement,</hi> which had the hearing and puniſhing of ſmaller matters. Secondly, The Court of three and twenty, here called, <hi>The Councell,</hi> which had the hearing and puniſhing of crimes of a higher nature. And thirdly, Of the higheſt Court of all, conſiſting of threeſcore and eleven, which they called their <hi>Sane drim,</hi> which Judged the higheſt matters, and puniſhed by death it ſelfe, whether by hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, beheading, ſtoning, or burning in <hi>Gehenna,</hi> before mentioned; he cleerly ſheweth, that there are great differences of ſin, and ſinners; and ſo
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:59533:66"/>there ſhall be alſo of puniſhments proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, under which the damned ſhall be held, and tormented in Hell for evermore. Unto which, the enlargement of <hi>Tophet,</hi> by the deſtruction of this world, in the great Conflagration, ſhall be much conducing, in giving convenient roome for it. And as the puniſhment, and torment of the damned in Hell ſhall be of divers, and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent meaſures, and degrees; <hi>Potentes potentèr cruciabuntur:</hi> Mighty men ſhall be mightily tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented; ſo, that the joy and glory of the Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall Inhabitants, ſhall be as different, in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and degree, is clearly revealed in Scripture. <hi>They that be wiſe, ſhall ſhine as the brightneſs of the Firmament, and they that turne many to righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſhall ſhine as the Starrs for ever and ever,</hi> Daniel 12.3. Which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. further confirmes, and more cleerly explicates this, <hi>There is one glory of the Sunne, another of the Moone, and another glory of the Starrs: for one Starr differeth from another Starr in glory,</hi> ver. 41. And then to prevent all miſtakes, and diſputes about it, he applyes it to this very purpoſe, <hi>verſe</hi> 42. <hi>Even ſo is the Reſurrection from the dead.</hi> And to this doth this Text of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> well agree, where it ſayes, <hi>We look
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:59533:66"/>for new Heavens,</hi> in the Plurall Number, (who knows how many) Ethereall Heavens, but he that made them? but Heavens they are, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore more then one, and this neceſſary for two Reaſons: Firſt, for the vaſt ſpaces that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to diſpoſe of the Caeleſtiall Inhabitants in, ſpaces which no man can meaſure for mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, which no man can number.</p>
               <p>Secondly, For the orderly diſpoſing of them in thoſe Heavens according to the dignity, and glory; the purity, and holineſs of thoſe that ſhall be placed in them. <hi>For as one Starr;</hi> ſo, <hi>one Heaven, differeth from another in glory. In my Fathers Houſe are many Manſions;</hi> thoſe Manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons not of equall beauty and magnificence; variety of Manſions for variety of Inhabitants; to ſome are reſerved Crowns, to other Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rells; ſome are clothed in White, the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate <hi>pediſſequae</hi> of the Lambe, which follows him whetherſoever he goeth: others attend at a farther diſtance. In the ſecond and third Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> there are ſeven ſeverall rewards aſſigned <hi>to them that overcome.</hi> In the nineteenth of Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> we ſee, upon the Account given by the ſervants of the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:59533:67"/>of the Talents committed to their truſt, <hi>One is made Ruler over ten Cities: another over five:</hi> every one hath his reward (according to his care and faithfulneſs) proportioned unto him. But what need we multiply words, in a caſe ſo cleer; conſider but the preſent ſtate of the Caeleſtiall Inhabitants, the holy Angels, now in glory; and from thence you will eaſily col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, what the ſtate of the Saints ſhall be after the Reſurrection: you will finde them diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted into ſeverall Claſſes, or Orders of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, in dignity and glory, one above another. For we reade of Angells, and Arch-Angells, of Cherubims, and Seraphims, of Thrones, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, Principalities, Powers, &amp;c. all which are ſo many Orders, and ſeverall Degrees of Angells excelling one another in dignity and glory. And if there be ſuch graduall diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons now, of the Angells divided, and diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into ſo many Orders, one above another in the Caeleſtiall Hierarchy; certainly much more muſt it needs be ſo, after the Reſurrection, when the number of the Caeleſtiall Inhabitants ſhall be ſo infinitely augmented by the acceſs of all the Saints, and elect people of God, which have
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:59533:67"/>been from the beginning of the world, and ſhall be to the laſt man that ſhall ſtand upon the Earth at that day. And it were ſtrange, That all theſe ſhould be limited to one Heaven to be diſpoſed in, which is all that ſome of you ſeem to allow: but that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> hath better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd us in the Text, when he ſayes, <hi>We look for new Heavens,</hi> Heavens in the Plurall, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens enough for the Creator to diſpoſe of all his people in, and to ſort them ſo, as that they ſhall all be in thoſe Heavens, which are moſt conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for them, and ſuitable to them, and for them to be Inhabitants in, and all theſe new too; not becauſe then newly Created: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we ſhall then newly take Poſſeſſion of them, and ſo they ſhall be new to us; not in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>For they were Created of old, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, from the foundation of the World.</hi> Let our Saviours own words, giving poſſeſſion of them, ſatisfie, and ſilence all further diſpute, or queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onings in this matter, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.34. with which I ſhut up this Diſcourſe, <hi>Come ye bleſſed Children of my Father, enter into the Inheritance of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome prepared for you, from the foundation of the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
